<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Dr JOANNA BAGNIEWSKA</title>
	<atom:link href="/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>zoologist &#124; science communicator </description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 11:28:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9.6</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/cropped-PhotoAKrajewski-3-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Dr JOANNA BAGNIEWSKA</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Nowe trendy wśród kociarzy: kolorowa kryza i śliniak z neoprenu. &#8220;Kot wstydzi się wyjść w tym na miasto&#8221;</title>
		<link>/2018/05/15/nowe-trendy-wsrod-kociarzy-kolorowa-kryza-i-sliniak-z-neoprenu-kot-wstydzi-sie-wyjsc-w-tym-na-miasto/</link>
		<comments>/2018/05/15/nowe-trendy-wsrod-kociarzy-kolorowa-kryza-i-sliniak-z-neoprenu-kot-wstydzi-sie-wyjsc-w-tym-na-miasto/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2018 22:06:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[blu]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[O zwierzętach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Po polsku]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gazeta Wyborcza]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[koty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ochrona gatunków]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2041</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Artykuł Martyny Śmigiel w Gazecie Wyborczej &#124; Sekcja kociarzy pochwaliła się w redakcji nowym gadżetem: kryzą dla kotów. Psiarze i ci bez zwierząt wobec nowego wynalazku byli raczej sceptyczni, a nawet zasiali defetyzm: czy ta kryza to czasem nie jest zwykły marketingowy bubel wciskany zatroskanym hodowcom kotów, który tylko ładnie...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em><a href="http://warszawa.wyborcza.pl/warszawa/7,54420,23231035,wychodzisz-z-kotem-na-spacer-powinienes-zalozyc-mu-kryze-zwierz.html">Artykuł <span class="art-author">Martyny Śmigiel w Gazecie Wyborczej </span></a></em><a href="http://warszawa.wyborcza.pl/warszawa/7,54420,23231035,wychodzisz-z-kotem-na-spacer-powinienes-zalozyc-mu-kryze-zwierz.html"><span class="art-author">|</span></a></p>
<p><strong>Sekcja kociarzy pochwaliła się w redakcji nowym gadżetem: kryzą dla kotów. Psiarze i ci bez zwierząt wobec nowego wynalazku byli raczej sceptyczni, a nawet zasiali defetyzm: czy ta kryza to czasem nie jest zwykły marketingowy bubel wciskany zatroskanym hodowcom kotów, który tylko ładnie wygląda i nabija kasę producentom? W imieniu wszystkich miejskich kociarzy &#8211; sprawdzamy</strong>.</p>
<p class="art_paragraph">Tajemniczo brzmiąca kryza to nic innego jak kolorowa opaska z falbaną przypominającą gumkę aksamitkę. Kryzę wkłada się kotu na szyję, gdy wybiera się on na spacer na zewnątrz. Kot musi się przecież wybiegać, wdrapać na drzewo, a także – o zgrozo! – zapolować. Taka już kocia natura – są drapieżnikami, nawet te na co dzień mieszkające w czterech ścianach. Koty polują więc na myszy, szczury, ale też ryjówki, młode zające czy króliki, a także ptaki oraz żaby i inne gady. Swoje ofiary rzadko nawet zjadają, sycą nimi raczej instynkty łowieckie. Co gorsza, upolowane zwierzęta traktują jak wojenne trofeum, którym chwalą się przed swoimi właścicielami. To też dowód na ich przywiązanie. Problem w tym, że na wycieraczce czy dywanie zdycha nam niczemu winny ptak lub gryzoń. Czy kryza może temu zapobiec?</p>
<h2 class="art_sub_title">Nie chronią ssaków</h2>
<p class="art_paragraph">Dr Joanna Bagniewska, zoolożka i wykładowczyni University of Reading w Wielkiej Brytanii, powołuje się na badania, zgodnie z którymi założenie kotu kolorowej kryzy zmniejsza liczbę upolowanych przez niego ptaków 19-krotnie na wiosnę, gdy wykluwają się młode, oraz trzykrotnie jesienią. Bo kryza działa głównie na ptaki. Są one wzrokowcami, reagują przede wszystkim na bodźce wizualne. – Koty mają szare, raczej neutralne w środowisku kolory. Ptak natychmiast wychwyci coś nienaturalnie kolorowego. I ma czas, by uciec przed drapieżnikiem, który chce go upolować – wyjaśnia dr Bagniewska.</p>
<p class="art_paragraph">Dodaje, że kryzy niestety nie chronią tak skutecznie ssaków. One posługują się przede wszystkim słuchem i węchem, praktyczne będzie więc założenie kotu na szyję zarówno kryzy, jak i klasycznego dzwoneczka, który ostrzega zwierzęta dźwiękiem. No, chyba że chcemy pozbyć się samych myszy.</p>
<h2 class="art_sub_title">Mechanizm szybko uwalniający</h2>
<p class="art_paragraph">Dr Bagniewska podpowiada, że kota można ubrać jeszcze w kolorowy śliniak z neoprenu. – Zawsze się śmieję, że jest skuteczny, bo kot po prostu wstydzi się w nim wyjść na miasto. Badania z Nowej Zelandii pokazują, że takie śliniaki zmniejszają prawdopodobieństwo upolowania przez kota ptaka aż o 81 proc. – podkreśla.</p>
<p>I jeszcze rada dla wychowanków Adama Słodowego: – Nie współpracuję z producentami obróżek, ale polecam kupienie profesjonalnej obroży zamiast ubierania kota w kolorową gumkę aksamitkę, mimo że wyglądają podobnie. Kryzy mają mechanizm szybko uwalniający, jeśli się za nie mocno pociągnie, odpadają. To zapewnia kotu bezpieczeństwo, gdy wspina się po drzewach i mógłby nieopatrznie powiesić się na takiej obroży – przestrzega dr Bagniewska.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2018/05/15/nowe-trendy-wsrod-kociarzy-kolorowa-kryza-i-sliniak-z-neoprenu-kot-wstydzi-sie-wyjsc-w-tym-na-miasto/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>White nose syndrome is killing millions of bats via a contagious fungus – here’s how to stop it</title>
		<link>/2018/03/21/white-nose-syndrome-is-killing-millions-of-bats-via-a-contagious-fungus-heres-how-to-stop-it/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 23:27:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[My writing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bats]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fungal diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Conversation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WNS]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1781</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[My article for The Conversation &#124; A dangerous fungus has been sweeping across North America with devastating consequences. In the past decade, between 5m and 7m bats in the US and Canada have been wiped out as a result of the fungal disease known as white nose syndrome, which alters their...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wrapper">
<div class="grid-twelve large-grid-eleven">
<div class="top">
<aside class="grid-two content-share"><em>My article for <a href="https://theconversation.com/white-nose-syndrome-is-killing-millions-of-bats-via-a-contagious-fungus-heres-how-to-stop-it-91698">The Conversation </a></em><a href="https://theconversation.com/white-nose-syndrome-is-killing-millions-of-bats-via-a-contagious-fungus-heres-how-to-stop-it-91698">|</a></aside>
<aside></aside>
<aside></aside>
<aside class="grid-two content-share"><strong>A dangerous fungus has been sweeping across North America with devastating consequences. In the past decade, between 5m and 7m bats in the US and Canada have been wiped out as a result of the fungal disease known as white nose syndrome, which alters their behaviour in potentially deadly ways. But the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-017-02441-z">latest research</a> shows there might be hope for researchers trying to battle the disease, following the discovery that UV light appears to destroy the fungus’s DNA.</strong></aside>
<aside></aside>
</div>
<div class="grid-ten large-grid-nine grid-last content-body content entry-content instapaper_body">
<p>White nose syndrome is caused by the fungus <em>Pseudogymnoascus destructans</em>, which grows on the bats’ muzzles (hence the name) and other hairless body parts including wings, and <a href="https://bmcbiol.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1741-7007-8-135">causes skin lesions</a>. <em>P. destructans</em> is psychrophilic, meaning it thrives in cold temperatures between 4℃ and 20℃. This means it affects bats during hibernation.</p>
<p><span id="more-1781"></span></p>
<p>The itchy, painful lesions cause infected bats to repeatedly wake from hibernation, leaving them confused and causing them to display <a href="http://www.batcon.org/our-work/regions/contact-bci/usa-canada/white-nose-syndrome">highly unusual behavior</a>, such as flying outside during daylight in nearly freezing temperatures. The cold, lack of food and abnormal activity leads to bats depleting their winter fat reserves, and starving, dehydrating or freezing to death. As a result, the disease can kill between <a href="https://www.nature.com/news/2010/100113/full/463144a.html">90% and 100%</a> of bats in affected hibernating colonies.</p>
<p>Out of the 47 bat species native to the US and Canada, over half rely on hibernation for survival. <a href="https://www.whitenosesyndrome.org/about/bats-affected-wns">Nine of these species</a> (including two endangered and one threatened) already show symptoms of white nose syndrome. <em>P. destructans</em> has also been found in another six species (including one endangered) that don’t yet show symptoms. The little brown bat (<em>Myotis lucifugus</em>), once the most common bat in North America, is now predicted to face <a href="http://science.sciencemag.org/content/329/5992/679">regional extinction</a>.</p>
<p>Bats normally live a long time and produce only a single pup each year, so affected species are unlikely to recover quickly. Not only is this bad for biodiversity, but it could also have a serious economic impact on humans. In temperate regions, bats eat up to 600 insects a night and so provide a vital pest-control service for North American farmers, effectively worth <a href="http://science.sciencemag.org/content/332/6025/41">US$3.7 billion a year</a>.</p>
<h5>How did this bat-astrophe come about?</h5>
<p><em>P. destructans</em> has probably co-existed with bats in Eurasia for <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-017-02441-z">millions of years</a>. As a result, these bats have evolved defences against the fungus. So in this part of the world, despite the occasional mild outbreak of white nose syndrome, the disease <a href="http://www.cell.com/trends/ecology-evolution/fulltext/S0169-5347(11)00192-3">doesn’t significantly impact entire groups of bats</a>. But when <em>P. destructans</em> was introduced to the previously unexposed American bats, the effects were disastrous.</p>
<p>White nose syndrome was discovered in North America <a href="http://science.sciencemag.org/content/323/5911/227">in 2006</a>. We know that the fungus was most likely spread by human activity because the North American fungus is <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0960982215000792">almost genetically identical</a> to some of the samples found in Europe. Also, bats don’t migrate between the two continents and some of the distances between contaminated caves in the US are longer than the flying range of affected bats. On top of that, the first reports of white nose syndrome came from a <a href="https://wwwnc.cdc.gov/eid/article/16/8/10-0002_article">popular tourist cave near Albany, New York</a>. So the fungus probably spread via contaminated clothing and caving equipment from tourists visiting affected areas.</p>
<p>Since then, white nose syndrome has become one of the most severe wildlife diseases ever recorded. Yet there may literally be a light at the end of the tunnel. A <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-017-02441-z">research team from the US Forest Service</a> has discovered that <em>P. destructans</em> is extremely sensitive to ultra-violet light, particularly to UV-C light that kills germs but doesn’t cause skin cancer. They found that moderate doses of UV-C light killed over 99% of the fungus, and that even low doses killed 85%.</p>
<p>The effect is so potent because UV light destroys the fungus’s DNA, and, unlike <a href="https://bmcgenomics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2164-15-6">related fungi</a>, <em>P. destructans</em> can’t repair the damage. Further tests are on the way to check whether UV light causes any damage to the bats themselves. But the fact that UV-C light has already been used in treatments of <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1365-2133.2008.08549.x/abstract;jsessionid=DACFFB496B5103A02CDAC89BD89CB96F.f01t02">other fungal infections</a> in mammals means the discovery is very promising.</p>
<p>Managing wildlife diseases can be difficult and expensive. Think of how hard it would be to apply fungicide skin cream to tens of thousands of bats hanging from the top of a cave. But shining a simple hand-held UV-C light source on them would be much easier. So this research could have huge implications for protecting North American bats.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><!--more--></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Polscy naukowcy w Wielkiej Brytanii: „Keep calm and curie on”</title>
		<link>/2018/03/03/polscy-naukowcy-w-wielkiej-brytanii-keep-calm-and-curie-on/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 11:46:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[blu]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Moje teksty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Po polsku]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Polacy w UK]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Społeczeństwo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[British Council]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Młodzi naukowcy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Polska nauka]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2234</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mój esej dla British Council, do tomiku &#8220;Ponad granicami: Wielka Brytania – Polska&#8221; z okazji 80-lecia British Council w Polsce &#124; Kiedy w 2006 roku, dwa lata po wstąpieniu Polski do Unii Europejskiej i otwarciu dla Polaków brytyjskiego rynku pracy, pierwszy raz przyjechałam do Wielkiej Brytanii, krążył tu następujący dowcip....]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><strong><em>Mój esej dla British Council, do tomiku <a href="https://www.britishcouncil.pl/sites/default/files/ponad_granicami_wielka_brytania_-_polska._wspolne_sprawy_wspolne_wyzwania_0.pdf">&#8220;Ponad granicami: Wielka Brytania – Polska&#8221;</a> z okazji <a href="https://www.britishcouncil.pl/en/events/essays-crossing-points-uk-poland-common-interests-shared-concerns">80-lecia British Council w Polsce</a></em></strong> |</div>
<div></div>
<div>Kiedy w 2006 roku, dwa lata po wstąpieniu Polski do Unii Europejskiej i otwarciu dla Polaków brytyjskiego rynku pracy, pierwszy raz przyjechałam do Wielkiej Brytanii, krążył tu następujący dowcip.</div>
<div>Dyrektor brytyjskiego hotelu szuka sprzątacza, na ogłoszenie odpowiada jakiś mężczyzna. – Skąd jesteś? – pyta go dyrektor. – Z Polski – pada odpowiedź. – Ach, z Polski! – odpowiada dyrektor. – Z czego robiłeś doktorat?</div>
<div>Ten gorzki żart dobrze oddaje charakter wielkiej gospodarczej migracji po roku 2004. Różnica w zarobkach między Polską a Wielką Brytanią była kolosalna. Opowiadano historie o polskich lekarzach, którzy w tygodniu pracowali na Wyspach jako sprzątacze, a na weekendy wracali na dyżur do Polski. Jedna z gazet opublikowała zdjęcie grupy polskich bezdomnych, śpiących w śpiworach na Victoria Station, podpisane: „Od lewej: inżynier, lekarz, architekt, prawnik”. Bez względu na posiadane doświadczenie i wykształcenie Polacy w Wielkiej Brytanii zgłaszali się do najpodlejszych prac, żeby tylko związać koniec z końcem.</div>
<div>W ciągu kilku lat ta sytuacja uległa zmianie. Po pierwsze, polscy imigranci – coraz lepiej władający angielskim i orientujący się</div>
<div>na brytyjskim rynku pracy, tworzący sieci wsparcia – zaczęli wspinać się po ekonomicznej drabinie. Po drugie, wielu Polaków (w tym naukowców) przeniosło się do Wielkiej Brytanii, żeby pracować w swoich dziedzinach. Po trzecie, członkostwo w Unii Europejskiej sprawiło, że opłaty za studia dla Polaków zrównały się z opłatami dla Brytyjczyków, więc znacząco wzrosła liczba polskich studentów na brytyjskich uczelniach. W niniejszym eseju chciałabym przyjrzeć się zagadnieniu międzynarodowej migracji w świecie nauki, szczególnie w obrębie nauk ścisłych, w Polsce i Wielkiej Brytanii.</div>
<div>Mój przyjazd do Wielkiej Brytanii to trzeci przypadek z opisanych wyżej – dopiero co zrobiłam licencjat, miałam zacząć studia magisterskie na wydziale zoologicznym Uniwersytetu Oksfordzkiego. Na tej uczelni studiowało wówczas zaledwie 81 polskich studentów. Kilka lat wcześniej, przed wstąpieniem Polski do Unii Europejskiej, liczba Polaków na Oksfordzie była raczej stała i wynosiła około 20 osób rocznie. Od tamtego czasu następuje stały wzrost: w 2009 roku na Oksfordzie studiowało 150 polskich studentów; w roku 2014 – 200; w 2017 – 250 (dane według statystyk Uniwersytetu Oksfordzkiego). Dzieje się tak nie tylko z powodu dużej liczby zgłaszających się, ale także w związku z licznymi programami mentorskimi (np. Project Access, The Kings Foundation), które ułatwiają studentom i absolwentom składanie wniosków.</div>
<div>Tak ciągłego wzrostu nie widać w przypadku ogólnej liczby polskich studentów w Wielkiej Brytanii. To prawda, że po wstąpieniu Polski do Unii Europejskiej liczba ta wzrosła ponaddwukrotnie (z 965 Polaków studiujących w Wielkiej Brytanii w roku 2003 do 2185 w roku 2004) i rosła nadal, aż do 9145 w roku 2008. Wtedy jednak, zapewne z powodu światowego kryzysu finansowego, liczba Polaków w brytyjskich instytucjach edukacyjnych gwałtownie spadła – stabilizując się na poziomie 5202 w latach 2012-2014. Od tamtego czasu zaczęła znowu powoli wzrastać i sięgnęła 6585 w roku 2016 – co można interpretować</div>
<div>jako próbę „załapania się” na studia, zanim dojdzie do brexitu.</div>
<div>W ciągu zaledwie kilku lat doświadczyliśmy przejścia od migracji czysto ekonomicznej do „drenażu mózgów”, ucieczki kapitału ludzkiego.  Polacy przybywają do Wielkiej Brytanii nie tylko z powodu wysokich zarobków, ale też wielu możliwości, jakie daje</div>
<div>ten kraj. Jeśli chodzi o karierę naukową, rzeczywiście ma on wiele do zaoferowania – z 200 najlepszych uniwersytetów świata według QS World University Rankings 2018 aż 28 znajduje się w Wielkiej Brytanii.</div>
<div>Polskich i brytyjskich instytucji akademickich nie tylko jest dziś więcej niż kiedyś, ale są też lepiej zarządzane i ściślej współpracują. Polscy studenci założyli Kongres Polskich Stowarzyszeń Studenckich w Wielkiej Brytanii reprezentujący ich wspólne interesy. W 2008 roku organizowano tylko jedną coroczną konferencję studencką – Kongres Polskich Organizacji. Dziś jest ich co najmniej pięć, dotyczą różnych zagadnień: nauki (Science: Polish Perspectives), biznesu i ekonomii (LSE</div>
<div>Polish Economic Forum), innowacji i nowych technologii (Poland 2.0).</div>
<div>Wybór tematów nie jest przypadkowy – wydaje się (choć nie jest to żaden poparty danymi dowód, jedynie moja obserwacja), że po 2010 roku studenci częściej wybierają nauki ścisłe, techniczne i biznesowe niż humanistyczne. To logiczne – jeśli musisz zaciągnąć wysoki kredyt studencki, to czy będziesz go w stanie spłacić jako magister teologii? (Ta uwaga nie jest wymierzona w teologów – autorka tego tekstu jest przecież zoologiem, a zoologia też nie jest dziedziną, w której można zarobić wielkie pieniądze!).</div>
<div>Trzykrotny wzrost opłat za studia nie sprawił, o dziwo, że brytyjscy studenci zaczęli szukać doświadczeń akademickich za granicą, w krajach, w których edukacja wyższa jest darmowa albo bardzo tania (a koszty życia są znacznie niższe niż w Wielkiej Brytanii). Nie mówię o „dzikim Wschodzie” – pokrytej wiecznym lodem krainie pijących wódkę niedźwiedzi polarnych, jak wciąż postrzega Polskę wielu Brytyjczyków – ale o innych krajach, takich jak Niemcy, Szwecja czy Dania, gdzie nie tylko cudzoziemcy nie płacą czesnego, ale też nie brakuje kursów prowadzonych wyłącznie po angielsku.</div>
<div>Do niedawna Wielka Brytania znajdowała się w szczęśliwym położeniu – przyciągała najlepszych z całego świata, zarówno studentów, jak i badaczy. Przynosiło to korzyści nie tylko jednostkom (każdej narodowości), ale całej brytyjskiej nauce. Brytyjscy badacze (mam na myśli wszystkich, którzy prowadzą działalność naukową w Wielkiej Brytanii, nie tylko posiadaczy paszportów Zjednoczonego Królestwa) są znakomici w pozyskiwaniu europejskich grantów: za każdego funta wpłaconego przez Wielką Brytanię na naukę do wspólnej kasy UE brytyjscy naukowcy dostają prawie dwa funty w grantach. Obecne plany, by zagranicznym absolwentom brytyjskich uczelni trudniej było zostać w Wielkiej Brytanii, to strzał w stopę – to przecież właśnie wysoko wykwalifikowani, zintegrowani imigranci przyczyniają się do wzrostu gospodarczego kraju.</div>
<div>Badania naukowe, szczególnie w naukach ścisłych, są z samej swojej natury przedsięwzięciem zbiorowym. Międzynarodowe zespoły mają szersze perspektywy, bogatsze doświadczenie, więcej pomysłów. Artykuły będące owocem współpracy międzynarodowej docierają do liczniejszej publiczności, są powszechniej czytane i mają większy wpływ na społeczność naukową. Niestety, brexit utrudni współpracę międzynarodową. Nowe ograniczenia w swobodnym przepływie ludzi</div>
<div>i brak pewności w kwestii finansowania mogą sprawić, że pracownicy naukowi zaczną wyjeżdżać i teraz Wielka Brytania doświadczy „drenażu mózgów” – zwłaszcza w sytuacji, gdy Niemcy i Francja wyrastają na potęgi w naukach ścisłych</div>
<div>i technicznych. Brytyjczycy z pewnością będą musieli się postarać bardziej, jeśli będą chcieli nadal współpracować z innymi badaczami – z Europy i całego świata.</div>
<div>Polscy badacze pracujący za granicą mogą służyć jako dobry przykład w tej kwestii. Jedną z cennych inicjatyw, które pojawiły się ostatnio w Wielkiej Brytanii, jest SPP – Science: Polish Perspective. Projekt ruszył w roku 2012 i był efektem współpracy między Stowarzyszeniem Polskich Studentów na Uniwersytecie Oksfordzkim i jego odpowiednikiem w Cambridge. Jego celem miało być stworzenie platformy współpracy dla naukowców polskiego pochodzenia pracujących poza krajem. SPP organizuje coroczną konferencję, na zmianę w Oksfordzie i w Cambridge, gdzie prezentowane są wyniki badań z wielu dziedzin nauki, tak różnorodnych jak astronomia, biochemia, ekologia czy informatyka kwantowa. Prezentacje odbywają się w formacie TED-talk i nie tylko muszą spełniać najwyższe standardy naukowe, ale też być zrozumiałe dla słuchaczy, którzy nie są specjalistami. Pierwotnie konferencja miała trzy cele: jednoczyć polską diasporę naukową, prezentować najnowsze osiągnięcia i poprawiać wizerunek Polaków w Wielkiej Brytanii. Szybko się jednak okazało, że może stać się również platformą międzynarodowej, interdyscyplinarnej współpracy. Jest także wspaniałą okazją dla polskich instytucji do zaprezentowania polskim badaczom możliwości, jakie czekają na nich w ojczyźnie. Sześć lat później Science: Polish Perspectives i jej siostrzana organizacja Fundacja Polonium organizują regionalne spotkania w Niemczech, Włoszech, Belgii, Szwecji. Prowadzą projekty badawcze na temat potrzeb i aspiracji polskich badaczy pracujących poza ojczyzną. Tworzą most między Polską a polską diasporą naukową.</div>
<div>Badacze z Polski, rozproszeni po całej Europie i świecie, są niezwykle cenni. Z jednej strony działają jako ambasadorowie polskiej kultury i nauki, z drugiej – jako zewnętrzni eksperci. W ciągu ledwie kilku lat Polska zdołała zapewnić dobre warunki tym, którzy zdecydują się wrócić do kraju: wysokie granty na badania są coraz powszechniej dostępne zarówno dla powracających do ojczyzny Polaków, jak i dla cudzoziemców zainteresowanych pracą w Polsce.</div>
<div>Choć warunki finansowe stają się coraz lepsze, Polsce wciąż wiele brakuje, jeśli chodzi o społeczne aspekty imigracji. Życie cudzoziemca w Polsce nadal nie jest łatwe (i to zarówno z punktu widzenia logistycznego, kulturalnego, jak i językowego). Wprowadzenie tego typu zmian jest czasochłonne, ale w tej kwestii to Polska może nauczyć się czegoś od Wielkiej Brytanii. Na przykład tego, że jeśli warunki pracy w nauce staną się przyjaźniejsze dla kobiet, to zyskają na tym wszyscy pracownicy, a kraj stanie się atrakcyjniejszy – zarówno dla obcokrajowców, jak i dla Polaków. Sądzę, że Polsce przydałoby się więcej przejrzystości w codziennym życiu – począwszy od podawania wynagrodzenia w ogłoszeniach o pracę, przez uproszczenie procesów administracyjnych, po lepsze oznakowanie labiryntu warszawskich przejść podziemnych. Choć Polska bardzo dba o młodych rodziców (nawet lepiej niż Wielka Brytania), a przykładem mogą być choćby urlopy rodzicielskie, polskie żłobki i przedszkola nie są jeszcze gotowe na akceptację różnorodności – ani z punktu widzenia organizacyjnego, ani kulturowego. Wreszcie Polska bez wątpienia mogłaby się nauczyć od Wielkiej Brytanii skutecznego budowania wizerunku w sieci – czy to w kwestii narodowej marki (jak np. kampania „Britain Is Great”), promocji w mediach społecznościowych, czy informowania o możliwościach, jakie</div>
<div>oferuje. Dziś Polska zbyt polega na kontaktach osobistych, jeśli chodzi</div>
<div>o poszukiwanie pracy – outsiderom bez mocnych pleców jest o wiele</div>
<div>trudniej, bez względu na to, jak bardzo są zdeterminowani.</div>
<div>Podsumowując – Wielka Brytania może dowiedzieć się od Polski, jak stworzyć silną diasporę naukową, utrzymać ją i wykorzystać; z kolei Polska mogłaby się nauczyć od Wielkiej Brytanii, jak powinno wyglądać społeczeństwo atrakcyjne dla cudzoziemców</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Polish Academics in the UK: Keep Calm and Curie On</title>
		<link>/2018/03/03/polish-academics-in-the-uk-keep-calm-and-curie-on/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:15:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[blu]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[My writing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[British Council]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science. Polish Perspectives]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student conference]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2230</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[My essay for the British Council&#8217;s collection &#8220;Crossing Points: UK-Poland Common interests, shared concerns&#8221; &#124; When I first came to the UK, in 2006, two years after Polish accession to the EU and the opening of the British labour market to Poles, there was a popular joke going round. A British...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>My essay for the British Council&#8217;s collection </em><a href="https://www.britishcouncil.pl/sites/default/files/crossing_points_uk_-_poland._common_interests_shared_concerns_0.pdf"><em>&#8220;Crossing Points: UK-Poland Common interests, shared concerns&#8221;</em></a> |</strong></p>
<p>When I first came to the UK, in 2006, two years after Polish accession to the EU and the opening of the British labour market to Poles, there was a popular joke going round.</p>
<p>A British hotel manager puts out an advert for a cleaner. A man responds. The hotel manager asks where he is from. The man answers – Poland. The hotel manager then says: Aaah, Poland! So – what did you do your PhD in?</p>
<p>The joke is bittersweet in its capture of the phenomenon of the huge post-2004 economic migration. The difference in wages between Poland and the UK was so striking that we heard stories of Polish medical doctors working as cleaners in the UK during the week – for financial reasons – and only flying to Poland for the weekends to practice medicine. One newspaper published a photograph of Polish squatters sleeping in sleeping bags on the ground at Victoria Station, with the caption: “From the left, we see an engineer, a medical doctor, an architect and a lawyer”. Regardless of their experience and education, Poles were happy to cling onto the most menial jobs in the UK, to allow them to make ends meet.</p>
<p>But within a few years the profile of the migrants started to change. First of all, improving their English skills, developing stronger support networks and finding out more about life in the UK and British hiring culture allowed the current migrants to start climbing up the economic ladder. Secondly, a number of Poles (amongst them academics) deliberately moved to the UK to work in line with their qualifications. Thirdly, being part of the EU meant qualifying for domestic rather than international university fees, which lead to a drastic increase in the numbers of Polish university students in the UK. In this essay, I would like to take a closer look at the case of international movement in academia, particularly in science – with a special focus on Poland and the UK.</p>
<p>I arrived in the UK as an example of that third instance – a freshly minted Bachelor of Science, ready to start an MSc at Oxford University’s Zoology Department. At that time I was one of just 81 Polish students at the University of Oxford. A few years earlier, before Polish accession to the EU, the number of Poles enrolled at Oxford was rather constant, oscillating around 20. Since then, there has been a steady increase:  in 2009, the number of Polish students at the University exceeded 150, in 2014 – 200, and in 2017 – 250 (based on Oxford University Student Statistics, <a href="https://www1.admin.ox.ac.uk/aad/studentregistry/sdma/statistics/student/">https://www1.admin.ox.ac.uk/aad/studentregistry/sdma/statistics/student/</a>). I am very proud to see the growing numbers of Oxford Poles, achieved not only because of the high quality of applicants, but also thanks to numerous mentoring programmes (e.g. Project Access, The Kings Foundation) where current students and alumni assist candidates with their application process.</p>
<p>Such a continuous increase is not reflected in overall numbers of Polish students in the UK. True, after Poland joined the EU, the figure more than doubled (from 965 Poles studying throughout the UK in 2003 to 2185 in 2004), and continued to grow until peaking in 2008 at 9145. But then, presumably due to the global financial crisis followed by the tripling of student fees, the number of Poles at British institutions plummeted, reaching a trough of around 5200 between 2012 and 2014. Since then, the numbers started to slowly rise, and have reached 6585 in 2016 – which could be interpreted as a move to “get in” before the onset of Brexit.</p>
<p>In just a few years, we have witnessed a shift from the purely economic migration, to a “brain drain”, or human capital flight, of Poles who entered the UK not only for the income, but because of the numerous opportunities it offered. And in academic terms, Britain certainly has a lot to offer, with 28 of its universities ranking in the top 200 in the world.</p>
<p>Currently, Poles at British academic institutions are not only more numerous – they are also better organized and more united than they used to be. Polish students formed the Federation of Polish Student Societies in the UK, which represents their interests in a unified front. In 2008, there was one annual student conference – the Congress of Polish Societies; currently there are at least five events, ranging in topics from the sciences (Science: Polish Perspectives), through business and economics (LSE Polish Economic Forum) to innovation and new technologies (Poland 2.0). The choices of the subject matter are not accidental – I have observed (though this is anecdotal evidence rather than anything I can back by hard data) a stronger profiling of students post-2010, with many in the sciences, engineering and business, and fewer in the humanities. This is logical – if you have to take out a huge student loan, will you be able to repay it after a theology degree? (This remark is not meant as a dig at theologians – after all, the author of this essay is a zoologist, hardly a money-making career!).</p>
<p>Surprisingly enough, the tripled university fees have not prompted British students to seek academic experiences abroad, in countries where tuition is either free, or very cheap (and the living costs much more affordable than in Britain). I am not even suggesting a move to the Wild, Wild East – the permafrost-covered land of vodka-drinking polar bears that Poland still is in the eyes of many a Brit – but what about a much more civilized country, such as Germany, Sweden or Denmark, where not only is tuition free for foreigners, but there are numerous programs run entirely in English?</p>
<p>Until now, Britain has been in a very fortunate position of being able to attract high quality students and academics from around the world. The benefits were great not just for the individuals (British or international), but also for British science as a whole. British academics – and in this context I refer to ones doing research in Britain rather than holding a UK passport! – are incredibly successful at obtaining European grants: for every pound Britain spends on science in the EU, British scientists get two back in grant money. Attracting high quality academics is what made British science stand out. The current plans to make it more difficult for international students to stay in the UK after graduation is shooting oneself in the foot – after all, it is the highly skilled, well-integrated migrants that will really boost the country’s economy.</p>
<p>Research, particularly in the sciences, is by nature, collaborative. International teams have a broader range of perspectives, experiences and ideas. International co-authored papers have a substantially higher impact than domestic only papers. They get read more, and they have more influence on the scientific community and beyond. Yet Brexit is likely to make international collaborations more difficult. With increasing barriers to free movement, and uncertainty regarding science funding, British researchers may choose to move out, leaving Britain to face its own brain drain, particularly when countries such as Germany and France are emerging as scientific or engineering heavyweights. Brits will certainly need to make more of a conscious effort if they would like to continue to cooperate with research groups in Europe and beyond.</p>
<p>Polish scientists working abroad could perhaps set a useful example in this respect. One worthwhile initiative which appeared recently in the UK is the Science: Polish Perspectives conference and movement. The project started in 2012 as a cooperation between Oxford University Polish Society and its equivalent from The Other Place, with the idea of bringing together scientists of Polish descent working outside of Poland.  Science: Polish Perspectives is an annual conference, alternating between Oxford and Cambridge, showcasing research from scientific areas as diverse as astronomy and biochemistry, or quantum computing and ecology. The presentations follow a TED-talk format, and have to not only be of very high scientific quality, but also be comprehensible for a non-specialist (although scientific) audience. Initially, the aims of the conference were threefold: to unite Polish scientific diaspora, to showcase ground-breaking research, and to improve the image of Poles in the UK. However soon it became apparent that the platform can lead to interdisciplinary, international collaborations; it was also a great opportunity for Polish institutions to demonstrate opportunities they offer to academics hoping to return to their homeland.</p>
<p>Six years down the line, Science: Polish Perspectives, and its sister organisation, the Polonium Foundation, organise regional meet-ups in Germany, Italy, Belgium and Sweden. They run research projects investigating the needs and aspirations of Polish academics abroad. They form a bridge between Poland and its scientific diaspora.</p>
<p>While Polish scientists are scattered throughout Europe and beyond, Poland is trying to make the most of them. On one hand, they act as cultural and scientific ambassadors, on the other, they often provide the country with external expertise. At the same time, over the span of just a few years Poland has been able to offer good opportunities for returnees, with increasing availability of high quality grants targeting  both Poles moving back to their homeland, and foreigners interested in working in Poland.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, even as the financial conditions are becoming more attractive, Poland still has a lot of catching up to do when it comes to the social aspects of immigration. Being a foreigner in Poland is still not easy – logistically, culturally, linguistically – and this may be a big push factor for both foreigners and a lot of Poles with foreign life partners. Bringing about this type of change takes time – however this is an area in which Poland could take a leaf from Britain’s book. Very much like the fact that, say, making the working conditions in academia more women-friendly results in policies that benefit all employees, making a country more foreigner-friendly will make it more user-friendly for nationals as well. I believe that Poland could use a bit more transparency in everyday life – starting from revealing proposed salary bands on job adverts, through making administrative processes more straight-forward, down to perhaps providing clearer signage in the labyrinthine structures of Warsaw underpasses. While Poland has been very good (in fact, much better than the UK) at making provisions for young parents – for instance through its scheme of parental leaves – Polish kindergartens and schools are not yet ready to embrace diversity, from both the organisational and cultural perspectives. Finally, Poland certainly could take a leaf from Britain’s book when it comes to online presence – be it in the capacity of national branding (such as the “Britain is Great” campaign), strategies for a successful national presence in social media, or building awareness of the opportunities that it offers. Currently Poland relies too heavily on personal connections when it comes to advertising job posts – outsiders without a robust support network are starting at a significant disadvantage, no matter how willing they are to find work.</p>
<p>In summary, Britain can learn from Poland how to create and maintain – and make the most of! – a strong academic diaspora, while Poland can learn how to create a society attractive for foreigners.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Shattering the academic glass tank</title>
		<link>/2018/02/02/shattering-the-academic-glass-tank/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 23:05:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[blu]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[My writing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EAIE]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women in STEM]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2219</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[My article for the EAIE Forum &#8211; Our Gendered World &#124; The metaphor of a glass ceiling, an invisible, often unacknowledged barrier that keeps a certain demographic from career advancement, is often used in the context of women in science. The phenomenon is so globally widespread that it has given...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>My article for the <a href="https://www.eaie.org/our-resources/library/publication/Forum-Magazine/2018-spring-forum.html">EAIE Forum &#8211; Our Gendered World</a></em> |</p>
<p>The metaphor of a glass ceiling, an invisible, often unacknowledged barrier that keeps a certain demographic from career advancement, is often used in the context of women in science. The phenomenon is so globally widespread that it has given rise to the concept of a “Glass Ceiling Index”, an indicator used to quantify gender equity in science. The GCI is one of many measures employed by the European Commission in the SHE Figures document, outlining the current state of gender equality in research and innovation throughout the European Union.</p>
<p>The presence of women is, unsurprisingly, the lowest in STEM (science, technology, engineering and mathematics) fields, as these disciplines have traditionally attracted more male than female scholars on all academic levels. However, even in STEM subjects with a high intake of female undergraduates, such as biological sciences, there is a disproportionate lack of female progression onto next stages of academic career, despite high academic achievements of women at all levels. Thus, while the number of women is high at an undergraduate stage, the proportion decreases at each progression point – postgraduate, postdoctoral, lecturer – leaving very few females at the professorial level. This progressive drop-out is known as “the leaking pipeline”, and is both global and trans-disciplinary.</p>
<p><strong>Beyond undergrad</strong></p>
<p>Currently in many countries females comprise around 50% of undergraduate students; in Europe, the representation of women at this stage is often higher than of men – e.g. in Sweden it reaches 65%. Yet, according to the SHE Figures report, at the professorial level the proportion of women is very low, for the most part below 15%. Once again, the figures are most drastic in the STEM subjects, as while European humanities and social sciences find themselves with 30% and 23.5% of female full-time professors, these numbers stand at only 9.8% in engineering and technology, and 15.8% in the natural sciences.</p>
<p>What is more, there is a pronounced gender pay gap in academia. According to statistics from the UK collated by the University and College Union, in 2015-16, women on academic contracts earned, on average, 12% less than their male counterparts. In the US and Canada that figure was just under 14% for full professors (based on data from the U.S. Education Department and Canadian Association for University Teachers).</p>
<p>Many explanations have been put forward to account for the glass ceiling phenomenon and the resultant major underrepresentation of qualified women in leadership roles – institutional biases, implicit and direct discrimination (including outright sexism), exclusion from the Old Boys’ Club, lack of role models, difficult work-life choices, or lack of confidence in the women themselves. The contributing factors are so numerous and diverse, that two researchers, Kris De Welde and Sandra L. Laursen, suggested an alternative name for the difficulties women face in academia: the “glass obstacle course”.</p>
<p><strong>The glass fence</strong></p>
<p>Meanwhile, another “glass” problem arises – the “glass fences” keeping women out of collaborative, international projects. International collaborations are a fundamental part of research, particularly in STEM fields. Multi-national projects bring together varied expertise, background, facilities and perspectives. Publications co-authored by international teams have a substantially higher impact than domestic-only papers: they get a wider readership, are cited more often, and have more influence on the scientific community, policy makers and other stakeholders. In order to maximise their scientific output and impact, today’s researchers attempt to be as mobile as possible, often internationally. However, while in other areas, such as business, international mobility carries with it bonuses such as paying school fees for the children, or assisting with finding a job for the spouse, academia still assumes that the researcher is single, unattached, with no caring responsibilities. According to Katherine Zippel, associate professor of sociology at Northeastern University, women are triply disadvantaged when it comes to international mobility – they tend to have less access to international opportunities as they are less likely to obtain positions at better funded institutions; they are in non-tenured, less secure job positions then men, which hampers the creation of a stable international network, and finally, they are the ones who most often bear the brunt of family-related responsibilities.</p>
<p>As a result, women are less likely to participate in international collaborations (23.5% compared to 33% of men, in a study of doctoral recipients in academic positions in America). What is more, they are less likely to co-author publications with international colleagues, despite the overall growing trend in cross-national collaborations (as stated by Elsevier’s Gender in the Global Research Landscape report).  In STEM fields, this contributes to the ongoing underrepresentation of women.</p>
<p><strong>Breaking the glass</strong></p>
<p>One way of addressing gender inequality in British institutions is the Athena SWAN (Scientific Women’s Academic Network) charter, founded in 2005. It recognises and celebrates examples of good practice towards the advancement of gender equality in higher education and research. Some of the recognised actions include outreach and mentoring programmes, reducing bias in recruitment, devising flexible and part-time working schemes which ensure career progression, or providing better access to childcare. Initially, the programme was limited to STEM subjects; currently it has expanded to include other disciplines.</p>
<p>Similarly, mobility schemes such as the Marie Sklodowska-Curie Fellowship allow women to actively pursue an international career in science. Currently in dual-career households it is often the higher-earning partner who dictates the mobility strategy – therefore providing financial independence and promoting equal pay leads female scientists towards a much more international professional life.</p>
<p>Research by Mary Bonawitz and Nicole Andel shows that in 2009 the average age of American college professors was 59, and their gender male. Most of these professors will be retiring by the age of 70, creating a gap that may be filled by a new wave of an equally accomplished, if more diverse, professorial body. Creating a working environment which takes into account the needs of parents, carers, researchers with special needs, will be beneficial for the new academic generation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Stacja Nauka PR4</title>
		<link>/2018/01/12/stacja-nauka-pr4/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 23:09:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[blu]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[O zwierzętach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Po polsku]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nietoperze]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ochrona gatunków]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[syndrom bialego nosa]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2222</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[O chorobie nietoperzy opowiadam w Radiowej Czwórce. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>O chorobie nietoperzy opowiadam w <a href="https://www.polskieradio.pl/10/5366/Artykul/1987522,Stacja-Nauka-11-stycznia-godz-1204">Radiowej Czwórce</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Zoolog: zamknięciu ferm norek powinna towarzyszyć akcja uświadamiająca</title>
		<link>/2017/12/17/zoolog-zamknieciu-ferm-norek-powinna-towarzyszyc-akcja-uswiadamiajaca/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 21:26:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[O mojej pracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[O zwierzętach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Po polsku]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fermy futerkowe]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nauka w Polsce]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[norka amerykańska]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PAP (Polska Agencja Prasowa)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zwierzęta futerkowe]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1764</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Wywiad dla PAP &#8211; Nauka w Polsce. &#124; Zamknięcie ferm, w których hodowane są norki, miałoby sens, gdyby jednocześnie przeprowadzono akcje uświadamiające skierowane do konsumentów. Jeśli popyt na futra utrzyma się, problem przeniesie się do innych krajów &#8211; powiedziała PAP zoolog dr Joanna Bagniewska. Posłowie PiS złożyli w Sejmie projekt...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="titleAuthorWrapper">
<p class="title" style="text-align: justify;"><em>Wywiad dla <a href="http://naukawpolsce.pap.pl/aktualnosci/news%2C27281%2Czoolog-zamknieciu-ferm-norek-powinna-towarzyszyc-akcja-uswiadamiajaca.html">PAP &#8211; Nauka w Polsce</a>. </em>|<em><br />
</em></p>
</div>
<div class="field field--name-field-image field--type-image field--label-hidden imageWrapper article" style="text-align: justify;"></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;"></div>
<p class="field field--name-field-lead field--type-string-long field--label-hidden lead field--item" style="text-align: justify;"><strong>Zamknięcie ferm, w których hodowane są norki, miałoby sens, gdyby jednocześnie przeprowadzono akcje uświadamiające skierowane do konsumentów. Jeśli popyt na futra utrzyma się, problem przeniesie się do innych krajów &#8211; powiedziała PAP zoolog dr Joanna Bagniewska.</strong></p>
<div class="field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden field--item">
<p style="text-align: justify;">Posłowie PiS złożyli w Sejmie projekt nowelizacji ustawy o ochronie zwierząt, który przewiduje m.in. wprowadzenie zakazu hodowli i chowu zwierząt futerkowych w celu pozyskiwania futer. Zakaz miałby wejść w życie 1 stycznia 2022 r. Zapisom tym sprzeciwiają się przedstawiciele branży futerkowej.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8220;Cierpienie zwierząt i zagrożenie dla środowiska spowodowane przez hodowlę to podstawowe powody, dla których należałoby zakazać prowadzenia ferm norek&#8221; &#8211; powiedziała w rozmowie z PAP zoolog z Uniwersytetu w Reading, dr Joanna Bagniewska. Jak dodała, kluczowe jest przeprowadzenie wśród społeczeństwa akcji, która uświadomi problemy związane z hodowlą norek na futra.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8220;Jeżeli zakażemy hodowli w Polsce, a ludzie nadal będą chcieli posiadać futra &#8211; problem związany hodowlą norek przeniesie się do innych krajów, np. do Chin, gdzie różne gatunki zwierząt futerkowych hodowane są obecnie w gorszych warunkach, niż w Polsce&#8221; &#8211; zauważyła.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">W rozmowie z PAP ekspertka powiedziała, że norki amerykańskie, hodowane w Polsce na futra, to zwierzęta znakomicie przystosowane do drapieżnego stylu życia. Żyjąc w środowisku naturalnym polują zarówno w wodzie, na lądzie, jak i na drzewach. Są większe i sprawniejsze od swoich krewnych, norek europejskich, które w Polsce całkowicie wyginęły.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Zoolog podkreśliła, że nie da się zapewnić stuprocentowej szczelności ferm, a wydostanie się zwierząt do środowiska naturalnego jest realnym zagrożeniem. &#8220;W pewnych częściach Europy norki amerykańskie stanowią dla rodzimych zwierząt konkurencję pokarmową &#8211; co znaczy w praktyce, że poszukują tego samego rodzaju pokarmu&#8221; &#8211; stwierdziła. &#8211; &#8220;A ze względu na wielką skuteczność podczas polowań mogą się przyczynić wyniszczenia innych gatunków. Na przykład na wyspach zamieszkanych przez ptaki wodne norki czują się jak dziecko w sklepie ze słodyczami, potrafią tam zdziesiątkować populacje&#8221;.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Bagniewska przywołała też przypadek Wielkiej Brytanii, gdzie aktywiści, którym bliskie było dobro norek, włamywali się do ferm i wypuszczali je na wolność. &#8220;Ich intencje były dobre, ale wykonanie już nie &#8211; bo norki silnie zaburzyły lokalne środowisko naturalne&#8221; &#8211; podkreśliła.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">W ocenie dr Bagniewskiej stosunkowo proste byłoby podniesienie dobrostanu zwierząt: zapewnienie im większych, bardziej luźnych klatek. &#8220;Nie wyczerpuje to jednak podstawowego zagrożenia, jakim jest związane z hodowlą ryzyko wprowadzenia obcego i bardzo inwazyjnego gatunku do środowiska&#8221; &#8211; dodała.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">W przypadku ferm za duży problem uważa się też towarzyszący im, bardzo intensywny zapach. Wynika on z tego, że w przeciwieństwie do innych gatunków masowo hodowanych przez ludzi &#8211; są drapieżnikami, a co za tym idzie, zapach ich odchodów jest bardziej drażniący, niż w przypadku roślinożerców. Do tego dochodzi fetor mięsnej karmy oraz brudnych klatek, w których przetrzymywane są tysiące stłoczonych zwierząt &#8211; wskazała dr Bagniewska.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8220;Futra to towar luksusowy &#8211; nie są konieczne do życia i przetrwania. Mamy mnóstwo alternatyw dla pięknego ubioru, dlatego zamknięcie ferm nie powinno być większym problemem dla społeczeństwa&#8221; &#8211; podsumowała. (PAP)</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Autor: Szymon Zdziebłowski</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Edytor: Anna Ślązak</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>British Council webinar: Making Connections</title>
		<link>/2017/12/16/british-council-webinar-making-connections/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 22:41:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brexit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[British Council]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EU]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1769</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Making Connections: What is the future for collaboration and mobility of Early Career Researchers across Europe? Together with Professor Sir Martyn Poliakoff, I have taken part in a webinar organised by the British Council. We have discussed the future possibilities for early careers researchers in Europe. Here is a run-down of the...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4 class="js-post-title post-title">Making Connections: What is the future for collaboration and mobility of Early Career Researchers across Europe?</h4>
<p class="js-post-body post-body">Together with Professor Sir Martyn Poliakoff, I have taken part in a <a href="https://open.http.mp.streamamg.com/index.php/extwidget/preview/partner_id/2000617/uiconf_id/30010368/entry_id/0_rjrjeqxy/embed/auto?flashvars%5bstreamerType%5d=hds">webinar </a>organised by the British Council. We have discussed the future possibilities for early careers researchers in Europe.</p>
<p class="js-post-body post-body">Here is a run-down of the webinar with timings in case you want to jump straight to a particular section/question.</p>
<p class="js-post-body post-body"><a class="js-link post-link" href="https://www.linkedin.com/redir/redirect?url=http%3A%2F%2Fmp%2Estreamamg%2Ecom%2Ftiny%2F7cmh2&amp;urlhash=F8J1&amp;_t=tracking_anet" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://mp.streamamg.com/tiny/7cmh2</a></p>
<p>&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;<br />
01:41 &#8211; Introduction to the Context of this Webinar<br />
05:18 &#8211; Meet the Speakers<br />
06:40 &#8211; PANEL INTERVIEW<br />
&#8211; Q &#8211; What are your experiences during your early research career?<br />
11:25 &#8211; Q &#8211; What it is like to establish yourself as a mobile Early Career Researcher and what are the greatest challenges you face?<br />
14:38 &#8211; Q &#8211; What would you say a ‘gold standard’ approach to supporting mobility and international collaboration (in Europe) should look like?<br />
17:00 &#8211; Q &#8211; How can universities and research institutions help to continue cooperation during and after Brexit?<br />
20:25 &#8211; Q &#8211; What do you think are viable areas and routes to engage scientists from Europe, in carving out a way forward?<br />
23:17 &#8211; Q &#8211; Where do you feel individual scientists can and should get involved in the shaping of what European collaboration and mobility might look like in the future?<br />
25:42 &#8211; Q &#8211; What are your personal recommendations to the negotiators of Brexit?<br />
31:45 &#8211; Open Q&amp;A Session<br />
53:35 &#8211; Conclusion &amp; Next Steps.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Expanding the roles of women in STEM</title>
		<link>/2017/12/16/expanding-the-roles-of-women-in-stem/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 21:04:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[My writing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EAIE]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[leaking pipeline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women in STEM]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1762</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[My blog post on the European Association for International Education site.&#124; The fields of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), have traditionally attracted more male than female scholars on all academic levels. The disparity of interests between genders can be seen as early as secondary school. The resulting trend is,...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<header class="article-header">
<p class="byline vcard" style="text-align: justify;"><em>My blog post on the <a href="https://www.eaie.org/blog/roles-women-stem/">European Association for International Education</a> site.</em>|</p>
</header>
<section class="entry-content cf">
<p style="text-align: justify;"><strong>The fields of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), have traditionally attracted more male than female scholars on all academic levels. The d</strong><strong>isparity of interests between genders can be seen as early as secondary school. The resulting trend is, unsurprisingly, reflected in university applications – STEM disciplines tend to be dominated by male applicants. Additionally, mobile studen</strong><strong>ts in STEM fields are far more likely to be male. Today’s blog, from scientist Joanna Bagniewska, explores the reasons female students lose interest in the STEM fields and shares some optimistic insight into how some organisations are working to address this trend. </strong><span id="more-12505"></span></p>
<h2 style="text-align: justify;">Losing interest at an early age</h2>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><a href="https://www.accenture.com/gb-en/blogs/blogs-get-more-women-digital-careers" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A study conducted in February this year</a> showed that female students report a significant dip in the enjoyment of STEM subjects as they enter teenage years: while half of surveyed girls aged 7-11 considered Maths and Computer Science enjoyable and fun, this proportion dropped to 31% and 36% respectively in respondents aged 11-14. The above finding is coupled with the fact that more than half of teachers (57%) and parents (52%) admit to having made gender stereotypes in relation to STEM.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">At university level, even in STEM subjects with a high intake of female undergraduates, there is a concern with retention of students, and ensuring that they do not drop out at any stage of their career. While the number of women in subjects such as biological sciences is high at an undergraduate stage, the proportion decreases at each progression point – postgraduate, postdoctoral, lecturer – leaving very few females at the professorial level.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: justify;">Institutional biases or individual burdens?</h2>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Many explanations have been put forward to account for this disproportion – including institutional biases, implicit and direct discrimination, lack of role models or lack of confidence in the women themselves. However, <a href="http://ftp.iza.org/dp10947.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">research published in August</a> shows that women are in fact more resilient than one might expect. Factors such as high school academic preparation, faculty gender ratio, or performance in the core subjects appear to have an equal effect on males and females, in terms of the risk of switching majors. Stereotyping a field as ‘masculine’ also seems to have no profound effect on the women in it. However, while individual factors appear to have no effect, their combination – particularly low grades, gender composition of class and external stereotyping signals – is a strong enough hit to drive women to drop out. It might therefore be worth investigating the ways of making the external environment a bit more ‘female friendly’ on an institutional level.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: justify;">Creating a female-friendly field</h2>
<p style="text-align: justify;">One way of addressing gender inequality in British institutions is the <a href="http://www.ecu.ac.uk/equality-charters/athena-swan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Athena SWAN (Scientific Women’s Academic Network) charter.</a> Founded in 2005, it recognises and celebrates examples of good practice towards the advancement of gender equality in higher education and research. Some of the recognised actions include outreach and mentoring programmes, reducing bias in recruitment, devising flexible and part-time working schemes which ensure career progression or providing better access to childcare. Initially, the programme was limited to STEM subjects; currently it has expanded to include other disciplines.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Similarly, mobility schemes such as the <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/research/mariecurieactions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Marie Sklodowska-Curie Fellowship</a> allow women to actively pursue an international career in science. Traditionally, the mobility of female researchers has been lower than that of their male peers, as the career progression of women has often been adjusted to accommodate the needs of the family. However currently, in dual-career households, it is often the higher-earning partner who dictates the mobility strategy. Providing financial independence and promoting equal pay leads female scientists towards a much more international professional life.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">We are at a point in history when the tables are turning – women are finding themselves encouraged, supported, and are suddenly beginning to grasp at the opportunities that have thus far been less accessible to them. A diversity of backgrounds, beliefs and opinions is an important contribution to the development of any field – as is retaining the potential of highly qualified employees.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><em>Joanna Bagniewska is a Zoologist, Science Communicator and Teaching Fellow at the University of Reading in the UK. </em></p>
</section>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Okrutny biznes</title>
		<link>/2017/08/21/okrutny-biznes/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2017 21:02:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Moje teksty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Po polsku]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[turystyka]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tygodnik Powszechny]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wywiad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zwierzęta]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1749</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mój artykuł w Tygodniku Powszechnym &#124; Tom Moorhouse, zoolog z Oksfordu: Turysta nie zastanawia się szczególnie nad losem zwierząt. Myśli, że „gdyby coś było nie tak, toby na to nie pozwolono”. &#8230; JOANNA BAGNIEWSKA: Dlaczego tak trudno zbadać, w jaki sposób poszczególne atrakcje oddziałują na gatunki? TOM MOORHOUSE: Od kilku lat popularne...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="panel-pane pane-views pane-full-article-limited">
<div class="pane-content">
<div class="view view-full-article-limited view-id-full_article_limited view-display-id-page view-full-article view-dom-id-f0b0be19523106a2c63431aafe3e80ac">
<div class="view-content">
<div class="views-row views-row-1 views-row-odd views-row-first views-row-last">
<div class="views-field views-field-field-summary">
<div class="field-content" style="text-align: justify;"><em>Mój artykuł w <a href="https://www.tygodnikpowszechny.pl/okrutny-biznes-35042">Tygodniku Powszechnym </a></em><a href="https://www.tygodnikpowszechny.pl/okrutny-biznes-35042">|</a></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;"></div>
<div class="field-content" style="text-align: justify;"><strong>Tom Moorhouse, zoolog z Oksfordu: Turysta nie zastanawia się szczególnie nad losem zwierząt. Myśli, że „gdyby coś było nie tak, toby na to nie pozwolono”.</strong></div>
</div>
<div class="views-field views-field-field-zdjecia-2" style="text-align: justify;"></div>
<div class="views-field views-field-body-1" style="text-align: justify;">&#8230;</div>
<div class="views-field views-field-body" style="text-align: justify;">
<div class="field-content">
<p><strong>JOANNA BAGNIEWSKA: Dlaczego tak trudno zbadać, w jaki sposób poszczególne atrakcje oddziałują na gatunki?</strong></p>
<p><strong>TOM MOORHOUSE:</strong> Od kilku lat popularne w RPA są „spacery z lwami”, dość kontrowersyjny proceder. Z jednej strony lwy są rozmnażane w niewoli, a nie wyłapywane, więc nie wpływa się na dziką populację zwierząt. Z drugiej strony – właściciele placówek ogłaszają, że koty po osiągnięciu dorosłości wesprą pulę genetyczną dzikich lwów, co byłoby korzystne z punktu ochrony gatunku, ale wydaje się mało prawdopodobne – oswojone zwierzęta nie nadają się do życia na wolności, jest to niebezpieczne zarówno dla nich, jak i dla ludzi. Co się więc dzieje z dorosłymi lwami? W tej chwili nie potrafimy sprawdzić.</p>
<p><strong>Czy takie atrakcje sprzyjają choć przekazywaniu wiedzy o życiu zwierząt?</strong></p>
<p>Jeśli ktoś nauczy się czegoś o biologii lwów&#8230; [ciąg dalszy wywiadu dostępny na stronie <a href="https://www.tygodnikpowszechny.pl/okrutny-biznes-35042">Tygodnika Powszechnego</a>]</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="panel-pane pane-views pane-ltd-warn">
<h2 class="pane-title" style="text-align: justify;"></h2>
<div class="pane-content" style="text-align: justify;"></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
