<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>In English &#8211; Dr JOANNA BAGNIEWSKA</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/in-english/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>zoologist &#124; science communicator </description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 11:28:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9.6</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/cropped-PhotoAKrajewski-3-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>In English &#8211; Dr JOANNA BAGNIEWSKA</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>White nose syndrome is killing millions of bats via a contagious fungus – here’s how to stop it</title>
		<link>/2018/03/21/white-nose-syndrome-is-killing-millions-of-bats-via-a-contagious-fungus-heres-how-to-stop-it/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 23:27:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[My writing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bats]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fungal diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Conversation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WNS]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1781</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[My article for The Conversation &#124; A dangerous fungus has been sweeping across North America with devastating consequences. In the past decade, between 5m and 7m bats in the US and Canada have been wiped out as a result of the fungal disease known as white nose syndrome, which alters their...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wrapper">
<div class="grid-twelve large-grid-eleven">
<div class="top">
<aside class="grid-two content-share"><em>My article for <a href="https://theconversation.com/white-nose-syndrome-is-killing-millions-of-bats-via-a-contagious-fungus-heres-how-to-stop-it-91698">The Conversation </a></em><a href="https://theconversation.com/white-nose-syndrome-is-killing-millions-of-bats-via-a-contagious-fungus-heres-how-to-stop-it-91698">|</a></aside>
<aside></aside>
<aside></aside>
<aside class="grid-two content-share"><strong>A dangerous fungus has been sweeping across North America with devastating consequences. In the past decade, between 5m and 7m bats in the US and Canada have been wiped out as a result of the fungal disease known as white nose syndrome, which alters their behaviour in potentially deadly ways. But the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-017-02441-z">latest research</a> shows there might be hope for researchers trying to battle the disease, following the discovery that UV light appears to destroy the fungus’s DNA.</strong></aside>
<aside></aside>
</div>
<div class="grid-ten large-grid-nine grid-last content-body content entry-content instapaper_body">
<p>White nose syndrome is caused by the fungus <em>Pseudogymnoascus destructans</em>, which grows on the bats’ muzzles (hence the name) and other hairless body parts including wings, and <a href="https://bmcbiol.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1741-7007-8-135">causes skin lesions</a>. <em>P. destructans</em> is psychrophilic, meaning it thrives in cold temperatures between 4℃ and 20℃. This means it affects bats during hibernation.</p>
<p><span id="more-1781"></span></p>
<p>The itchy, painful lesions cause infected bats to repeatedly wake from hibernation, leaving them confused and causing them to display <a href="http://www.batcon.org/our-work/regions/contact-bci/usa-canada/white-nose-syndrome">highly unusual behavior</a>, such as flying outside during daylight in nearly freezing temperatures. The cold, lack of food and abnormal activity leads to bats depleting their winter fat reserves, and starving, dehydrating or freezing to death. As a result, the disease can kill between <a href="https://www.nature.com/news/2010/100113/full/463144a.html">90% and 100%</a> of bats in affected hibernating colonies.</p>
<p>Out of the 47 bat species native to the US and Canada, over half rely on hibernation for survival. <a href="https://www.whitenosesyndrome.org/about/bats-affected-wns">Nine of these species</a> (including two endangered and one threatened) already show symptoms of white nose syndrome. <em>P. destructans</em> has also been found in another six species (including one endangered) that don’t yet show symptoms. The little brown bat (<em>Myotis lucifugus</em>), once the most common bat in North America, is now predicted to face <a href="http://science.sciencemag.org/content/329/5992/679">regional extinction</a>.</p>
<p>Bats normally live a long time and produce only a single pup each year, so affected species are unlikely to recover quickly. Not only is this bad for biodiversity, but it could also have a serious economic impact on humans. In temperate regions, bats eat up to 600 insects a night and so provide a vital pest-control service for North American farmers, effectively worth <a href="http://science.sciencemag.org/content/332/6025/41">US$3.7 billion a year</a>.</p>
<h5>How did this bat-astrophe come about?</h5>
<p><em>P. destructans</em> has probably co-existed with bats in Eurasia for <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-017-02441-z">millions of years</a>. As a result, these bats have evolved defences against the fungus. So in this part of the world, despite the occasional mild outbreak of white nose syndrome, the disease <a href="http://www.cell.com/trends/ecology-evolution/fulltext/S0169-5347(11)00192-3">doesn’t significantly impact entire groups of bats</a>. But when <em>P. destructans</em> was introduced to the previously unexposed American bats, the effects were disastrous.</p>
<p>White nose syndrome was discovered in North America <a href="http://science.sciencemag.org/content/323/5911/227">in 2006</a>. We know that the fungus was most likely spread by human activity because the North American fungus is <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0960982215000792">almost genetically identical</a> to some of the samples found in Europe. Also, bats don’t migrate between the two continents and some of the distances between contaminated caves in the US are longer than the flying range of affected bats. On top of that, the first reports of white nose syndrome came from a <a href="https://wwwnc.cdc.gov/eid/article/16/8/10-0002_article">popular tourist cave near Albany, New York</a>. So the fungus probably spread via contaminated clothing and caving equipment from tourists visiting affected areas.</p>
<p>Since then, white nose syndrome has become one of the most severe wildlife diseases ever recorded. Yet there may literally be a light at the end of the tunnel. A <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-017-02441-z">research team from the US Forest Service</a> has discovered that <em>P. destructans</em> is extremely sensitive to ultra-violet light, particularly to UV-C light that kills germs but doesn’t cause skin cancer. They found that moderate doses of UV-C light killed over 99% of the fungus, and that even low doses killed 85%.</p>
<p>The effect is so potent because UV light destroys the fungus’s DNA, and, unlike <a href="https://bmcgenomics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2164-15-6">related fungi</a>, <em>P. destructans</em> can’t repair the damage. Further tests are on the way to check whether UV light causes any damage to the bats themselves. But the fact that UV-C light has already been used in treatments of <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1365-2133.2008.08549.x/abstract;jsessionid=DACFFB496B5103A02CDAC89BD89CB96F.f01t02">other fungal infections</a> in mammals means the discovery is very promising.</p>
<p>Managing wildlife diseases can be difficult and expensive. Think of how hard it would be to apply fungicide skin cream to tens of thousands of bats hanging from the top of a cave. But shining a simple hand-held UV-C light source on them would be much easier. So this research could have huge implications for protecting North American bats.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><!--more--></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Polish Academics in the UK: Keep Calm and Curie On</title>
		<link>/2018/03/03/polish-academics-in-the-uk-keep-calm-and-curie-on/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:15:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[blu]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[My writing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[British Council]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science. Polish Perspectives]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student conference]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2230</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[My essay for the British Council&#8217;s collection &#8220;Crossing Points: UK-Poland Common interests, shared concerns&#8221; &#124; When I first came to the UK, in 2006, two years after Polish accession to the EU and the opening of the British labour market to Poles, there was a popular joke going round. A British...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>My essay for the British Council&#8217;s collection </em><a href="https://www.britishcouncil.pl/sites/default/files/crossing_points_uk_-_poland._common_interests_shared_concerns_0.pdf"><em>&#8220;Crossing Points: UK-Poland Common interests, shared concerns&#8221;</em></a> |</strong></p>
<p>When I first came to the UK, in 2006, two years after Polish accession to the EU and the opening of the British labour market to Poles, there was a popular joke going round.</p>
<p>A British hotel manager puts out an advert for a cleaner. A man responds. The hotel manager asks where he is from. The man answers – Poland. The hotel manager then says: Aaah, Poland! So – what did you do your PhD in?</p>
<p>The joke is bittersweet in its capture of the phenomenon of the huge post-2004 economic migration. The difference in wages between Poland and the UK was so striking that we heard stories of Polish medical doctors working as cleaners in the UK during the week – for financial reasons – and only flying to Poland for the weekends to practice medicine. One newspaper published a photograph of Polish squatters sleeping in sleeping bags on the ground at Victoria Station, with the caption: “From the left, we see an engineer, a medical doctor, an architect and a lawyer”. Regardless of their experience and education, Poles were happy to cling onto the most menial jobs in the UK, to allow them to make ends meet.</p>
<p>But within a few years the profile of the migrants started to change. First of all, improving their English skills, developing stronger support networks and finding out more about life in the UK and British hiring culture allowed the current migrants to start climbing up the economic ladder. Secondly, a number of Poles (amongst them academics) deliberately moved to the UK to work in line with their qualifications. Thirdly, being part of the EU meant qualifying for domestic rather than international university fees, which lead to a drastic increase in the numbers of Polish university students in the UK. In this essay, I would like to take a closer look at the case of international movement in academia, particularly in science – with a special focus on Poland and the UK.</p>
<p>I arrived in the UK as an example of that third instance – a freshly minted Bachelor of Science, ready to start an MSc at Oxford University’s Zoology Department. At that time I was one of just 81 Polish students at the University of Oxford. A few years earlier, before Polish accession to the EU, the number of Poles enrolled at Oxford was rather constant, oscillating around 20. Since then, there has been a steady increase:  in 2009, the number of Polish students at the University exceeded 150, in 2014 – 200, and in 2017 – 250 (based on Oxford University Student Statistics, <a href="https://www1.admin.ox.ac.uk/aad/studentregistry/sdma/statistics/student/">https://www1.admin.ox.ac.uk/aad/studentregistry/sdma/statistics/student/</a>). I am very proud to see the growing numbers of Oxford Poles, achieved not only because of the high quality of applicants, but also thanks to numerous mentoring programmes (e.g. Project Access, The Kings Foundation) where current students and alumni assist candidates with their application process.</p>
<p>Such a continuous increase is not reflected in overall numbers of Polish students in the UK. True, after Poland joined the EU, the figure more than doubled (from 965 Poles studying throughout the UK in 2003 to 2185 in 2004), and continued to grow until peaking in 2008 at 9145. But then, presumably due to the global financial crisis followed by the tripling of student fees, the number of Poles at British institutions plummeted, reaching a trough of around 5200 between 2012 and 2014. Since then, the numbers started to slowly rise, and have reached 6585 in 2016 – which could be interpreted as a move to “get in” before the onset of Brexit.</p>
<p>In just a few years, we have witnessed a shift from the purely economic migration, to a “brain drain”, or human capital flight, of Poles who entered the UK not only for the income, but because of the numerous opportunities it offered. And in academic terms, Britain certainly has a lot to offer, with 28 of its universities ranking in the top 200 in the world.</p>
<p>Currently, Poles at British academic institutions are not only more numerous – they are also better organized and more united than they used to be. Polish students formed the Federation of Polish Student Societies in the UK, which represents their interests in a unified front. In 2008, there was one annual student conference – the Congress of Polish Societies; currently there are at least five events, ranging in topics from the sciences (Science: Polish Perspectives), through business and economics (LSE Polish Economic Forum) to innovation and new technologies (Poland 2.0). The choices of the subject matter are not accidental – I have observed (though this is anecdotal evidence rather than anything I can back by hard data) a stronger profiling of students post-2010, with many in the sciences, engineering and business, and fewer in the humanities. This is logical – if you have to take out a huge student loan, will you be able to repay it after a theology degree? (This remark is not meant as a dig at theologians – after all, the author of this essay is a zoologist, hardly a money-making career!).</p>
<p>Surprisingly enough, the tripled university fees have not prompted British students to seek academic experiences abroad, in countries where tuition is either free, or very cheap (and the living costs much more affordable than in Britain). I am not even suggesting a move to the Wild, Wild East – the permafrost-covered land of vodka-drinking polar bears that Poland still is in the eyes of many a Brit – but what about a much more civilized country, such as Germany, Sweden or Denmark, where not only is tuition free for foreigners, but there are numerous programs run entirely in English?</p>
<p>Until now, Britain has been in a very fortunate position of being able to attract high quality students and academics from around the world. The benefits were great not just for the individuals (British or international), but also for British science as a whole. British academics – and in this context I refer to ones doing research in Britain rather than holding a UK passport! – are incredibly successful at obtaining European grants: for every pound Britain spends on science in the EU, British scientists get two back in grant money. Attracting high quality academics is what made British science stand out. The current plans to make it more difficult for international students to stay in the UK after graduation is shooting oneself in the foot – after all, it is the highly skilled, well-integrated migrants that will really boost the country’s economy.</p>
<p>Research, particularly in the sciences, is by nature, collaborative. International teams have a broader range of perspectives, experiences and ideas. International co-authored papers have a substantially higher impact than domestic only papers. They get read more, and they have more influence on the scientific community and beyond. Yet Brexit is likely to make international collaborations more difficult. With increasing barriers to free movement, and uncertainty regarding science funding, British researchers may choose to move out, leaving Britain to face its own brain drain, particularly when countries such as Germany and France are emerging as scientific or engineering heavyweights. Brits will certainly need to make more of a conscious effort if they would like to continue to cooperate with research groups in Europe and beyond.</p>
<p>Polish scientists working abroad could perhaps set a useful example in this respect. One worthwhile initiative which appeared recently in the UK is the Science: Polish Perspectives conference and movement. The project started in 2012 as a cooperation between Oxford University Polish Society and its equivalent from The Other Place, with the idea of bringing together scientists of Polish descent working outside of Poland.  Science: Polish Perspectives is an annual conference, alternating between Oxford and Cambridge, showcasing research from scientific areas as diverse as astronomy and biochemistry, or quantum computing and ecology. The presentations follow a TED-talk format, and have to not only be of very high scientific quality, but also be comprehensible for a non-specialist (although scientific) audience. Initially, the aims of the conference were threefold: to unite Polish scientific diaspora, to showcase ground-breaking research, and to improve the image of Poles in the UK. However soon it became apparent that the platform can lead to interdisciplinary, international collaborations; it was also a great opportunity for Polish institutions to demonstrate opportunities they offer to academics hoping to return to their homeland.</p>
<p>Six years down the line, Science: Polish Perspectives, and its sister organisation, the Polonium Foundation, organise regional meet-ups in Germany, Italy, Belgium and Sweden. They run research projects investigating the needs and aspirations of Polish academics abroad. They form a bridge between Poland and its scientific diaspora.</p>
<p>While Polish scientists are scattered throughout Europe and beyond, Poland is trying to make the most of them. On one hand, they act as cultural and scientific ambassadors, on the other, they often provide the country with external expertise. At the same time, over the span of just a few years Poland has been able to offer good opportunities for returnees, with increasing availability of high quality grants targeting  both Poles moving back to their homeland, and foreigners interested in working in Poland.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, even as the financial conditions are becoming more attractive, Poland still has a lot of catching up to do when it comes to the social aspects of immigration. Being a foreigner in Poland is still not easy – logistically, culturally, linguistically – and this may be a big push factor for both foreigners and a lot of Poles with foreign life partners. Bringing about this type of change takes time – however this is an area in which Poland could take a leaf from Britain’s book. Very much like the fact that, say, making the working conditions in academia more women-friendly results in policies that benefit all employees, making a country more foreigner-friendly will make it more user-friendly for nationals as well. I believe that Poland could use a bit more transparency in everyday life – starting from revealing proposed salary bands on job adverts, through making administrative processes more straight-forward, down to perhaps providing clearer signage in the labyrinthine structures of Warsaw underpasses. While Poland has been very good (in fact, much better than the UK) at making provisions for young parents – for instance through its scheme of parental leaves – Polish kindergartens and schools are not yet ready to embrace diversity, from both the organisational and cultural perspectives. Finally, Poland certainly could take a leaf from Britain’s book when it comes to online presence – be it in the capacity of national branding (such as the “Britain is Great” campaign), strategies for a successful national presence in social media, or building awareness of the opportunities that it offers. Currently Poland relies too heavily on personal connections when it comes to advertising job posts – outsiders without a robust support network are starting at a significant disadvantage, no matter how willing they are to find work.</p>
<p>In summary, Britain can learn from Poland how to create and maintain – and make the most of! – a strong academic diaspora, while Poland can learn how to create a society attractive for foreigners.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Shattering the academic glass tank</title>
		<link>/2018/02/02/shattering-the-academic-glass-tank/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 23:05:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[blu]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[My writing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EAIE]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women in STEM]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2219</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[My article for the EAIE Forum &#8211; Our Gendered World &#124; The metaphor of a glass ceiling, an invisible, often unacknowledged barrier that keeps a certain demographic from career advancement, is often used in the context of women in science. The phenomenon is so globally widespread that it has given...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>My article for the <a href="https://www.eaie.org/our-resources/library/publication/Forum-Magazine/2018-spring-forum.html">EAIE Forum &#8211; Our Gendered World</a></em> |</p>
<p>The metaphor of a glass ceiling, an invisible, often unacknowledged barrier that keeps a certain demographic from career advancement, is often used in the context of women in science. The phenomenon is so globally widespread that it has given rise to the concept of a “Glass Ceiling Index”, an indicator used to quantify gender equity in science. The GCI is one of many measures employed by the European Commission in the SHE Figures document, outlining the current state of gender equality in research and innovation throughout the European Union.</p>
<p>The presence of women is, unsurprisingly, the lowest in STEM (science, technology, engineering and mathematics) fields, as these disciplines have traditionally attracted more male than female scholars on all academic levels. However, even in STEM subjects with a high intake of female undergraduates, such as biological sciences, there is a disproportionate lack of female progression onto next stages of academic career, despite high academic achievements of women at all levels. Thus, while the number of women is high at an undergraduate stage, the proportion decreases at each progression point – postgraduate, postdoctoral, lecturer – leaving very few females at the professorial level. This progressive drop-out is known as “the leaking pipeline”, and is both global and trans-disciplinary.</p>
<p><strong>Beyond undergrad</strong></p>
<p>Currently in many countries females comprise around 50% of undergraduate students; in Europe, the representation of women at this stage is often higher than of men – e.g. in Sweden it reaches 65%. Yet, according to the SHE Figures report, at the professorial level the proportion of women is very low, for the most part below 15%. Once again, the figures are most drastic in the STEM subjects, as while European humanities and social sciences find themselves with 30% and 23.5% of female full-time professors, these numbers stand at only 9.8% in engineering and technology, and 15.8% in the natural sciences.</p>
<p>What is more, there is a pronounced gender pay gap in academia. According to statistics from the UK collated by the University and College Union, in 2015-16, women on academic contracts earned, on average, 12% less than their male counterparts. In the US and Canada that figure was just under 14% for full professors (based on data from the U.S. Education Department and Canadian Association for University Teachers).</p>
<p>Many explanations have been put forward to account for the glass ceiling phenomenon and the resultant major underrepresentation of qualified women in leadership roles – institutional biases, implicit and direct discrimination (including outright sexism), exclusion from the Old Boys’ Club, lack of role models, difficult work-life choices, or lack of confidence in the women themselves. The contributing factors are so numerous and diverse, that two researchers, Kris De Welde and Sandra L. Laursen, suggested an alternative name for the difficulties women face in academia: the “glass obstacle course”.</p>
<p><strong>The glass fence</strong></p>
<p>Meanwhile, another “glass” problem arises – the “glass fences” keeping women out of collaborative, international projects. International collaborations are a fundamental part of research, particularly in STEM fields. Multi-national projects bring together varied expertise, background, facilities and perspectives. Publications co-authored by international teams have a substantially higher impact than domestic-only papers: they get a wider readership, are cited more often, and have more influence on the scientific community, policy makers and other stakeholders. In order to maximise their scientific output and impact, today’s researchers attempt to be as mobile as possible, often internationally. However, while in other areas, such as business, international mobility carries with it bonuses such as paying school fees for the children, or assisting with finding a job for the spouse, academia still assumes that the researcher is single, unattached, with no caring responsibilities. According to Katherine Zippel, associate professor of sociology at Northeastern University, women are triply disadvantaged when it comes to international mobility – they tend to have less access to international opportunities as they are less likely to obtain positions at better funded institutions; they are in non-tenured, less secure job positions then men, which hampers the creation of a stable international network, and finally, they are the ones who most often bear the brunt of family-related responsibilities.</p>
<p>As a result, women are less likely to participate in international collaborations (23.5% compared to 33% of men, in a study of doctoral recipients in academic positions in America). What is more, they are less likely to co-author publications with international colleagues, despite the overall growing trend in cross-national collaborations (as stated by Elsevier’s Gender in the Global Research Landscape report).  In STEM fields, this contributes to the ongoing underrepresentation of women.</p>
<p><strong>Breaking the glass</strong></p>
<p>One way of addressing gender inequality in British institutions is the Athena SWAN (Scientific Women’s Academic Network) charter, founded in 2005. It recognises and celebrates examples of good practice towards the advancement of gender equality in higher education and research. Some of the recognised actions include outreach and mentoring programmes, reducing bias in recruitment, devising flexible and part-time working schemes which ensure career progression, or providing better access to childcare. Initially, the programme was limited to STEM subjects; currently it has expanded to include other disciplines.</p>
<p>Similarly, mobility schemes such as the Marie Sklodowska-Curie Fellowship allow women to actively pursue an international career in science. Currently in dual-career households it is often the higher-earning partner who dictates the mobility strategy – therefore providing financial independence and promoting equal pay leads female scientists towards a much more international professional life.</p>
<p>Research by Mary Bonawitz and Nicole Andel shows that in 2009 the average age of American college professors was 59, and their gender male. Most of these professors will be retiring by the age of 70, creating a gap that may be filled by a new wave of an equally accomplished, if more diverse, professorial body. Creating a working environment which takes into account the needs of parents, carers, researchers with special needs, will be beneficial for the new academic generation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>British Council webinar: Making Connections</title>
		<link>/2017/12/16/british-council-webinar-making-connections/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 22:41:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brexit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[British Council]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EU]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1769</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Making Connections: What is the future for collaboration and mobility of Early Career Researchers across Europe? Together with Professor Sir Martyn Poliakoff, I have taken part in a webinar organised by the British Council. We have discussed the future possibilities for early careers researchers in Europe. Here is a run-down of the...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4 class="js-post-title post-title">Making Connections: What is the future for collaboration and mobility of Early Career Researchers across Europe?</h4>
<p class="js-post-body post-body">Together with Professor Sir Martyn Poliakoff, I have taken part in a <a href="https://open.http.mp.streamamg.com/index.php/extwidget/preview/partner_id/2000617/uiconf_id/30010368/entry_id/0_rjrjeqxy/embed/auto?flashvars%5bstreamerType%5d=hds">webinar </a>organised by the British Council. We have discussed the future possibilities for early careers researchers in Europe.</p>
<p class="js-post-body post-body">Here is a run-down of the webinar with timings in case you want to jump straight to a particular section/question.</p>
<p class="js-post-body post-body"><a class="js-link post-link" href="https://www.linkedin.com/redir/redirect?url=http%3A%2F%2Fmp%2Estreamamg%2Ecom%2Ftiny%2F7cmh2&amp;urlhash=F8J1&amp;_t=tracking_anet" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://mp.streamamg.com/tiny/7cmh2</a></p>
<p>&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;<br />
01:41 &#8211; Introduction to the Context of this Webinar<br />
05:18 &#8211; Meet the Speakers<br />
06:40 &#8211; PANEL INTERVIEW<br />
&#8211; Q &#8211; What are your experiences during your early research career?<br />
11:25 &#8211; Q &#8211; What it is like to establish yourself as a mobile Early Career Researcher and what are the greatest challenges you face?<br />
14:38 &#8211; Q &#8211; What would you say a ‘gold standard’ approach to supporting mobility and international collaboration (in Europe) should look like?<br />
17:00 &#8211; Q &#8211; How can universities and research institutions help to continue cooperation during and after Brexit?<br />
20:25 &#8211; Q &#8211; What do you think are viable areas and routes to engage scientists from Europe, in carving out a way forward?<br />
23:17 &#8211; Q &#8211; Where do you feel individual scientists can and should get involved in the shaping of what European collaboration and mobility might look like in the future?<br />
25:42 &#8211; Q &#8211; What are your personal recommendations to the negotiators of Brexit?<br />
31:45 &#8211; Open Q&amp;A Session<br />
53:35 &#8211; Conclusion &amp; Next Steps.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Expanding the roles of women in STEM</title>
		<link>/2017/12/16/expanding-the-roles-of-women-in-stem/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 21:04:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[My writing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EAIE]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[leaking pipeline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women in STEM]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1762</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[My blog post on the European Association for International Education site.&#124; The fields of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), have traditionally attracted more male than female scholars on all academic levels. The disparity of interests between genders can be seen as early as secondary school. The resulting trend is,...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<header class="article-header">
<p class="byline vcard" style="text-align: justify;"><em>My blog post on the <a href="https://www.eaie.org/blog/roles-women-stem/">European Association for International Education</a> site.</em>|</p>
</header>
<section class="entry-content cf">
<p style="text-align: justify;"><strong>The fields of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), have traditionally attracted more male than female scholars on all academic levels. The d</strong><strong>isparity of interests between genders can be seen as early as secondary school. The resulting trend is, unsurprisingly, reflected in university applications – STEM disciplines tend to be dominated by male applicants. Additionally, mobile studen</strong><strong>ts in STEM fields are far more likely to be male. Today’s blog, from scientist Joanna Bagniewska, explores the reasons female students lose interest in the STEM fields and shares some optimistic insight into how some organisations are working to address this trend. </strong><span id="more-12505"></span></p>
<h2 style="text-align: justify;">Losing interest at an early age</h2>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><a href="https://www.accenture.com/gb-en/blogs/blogs-get-more-women-digital-careers" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A study conducted in February this year</a> showed that female students report a significant dip in the enjoyment of STEM subjects as they enter teenage years: while half of surveyed girls aged 7-11 considered Maths and Computer Science enjoyable and fun, this proportion dropped to 31% and 36% respectively in respondents aged 11-14. The above finding is coupled with the fact that more than half of teachers (57%) and parents (52%) admit to having made gender stereotypes in relation to STEM.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">At university level, even in STEM subjects with a high intake of female undergraduates, there is a concern with retention of students, and ensuring that they do not drop out at any stage of their career. While the number of women in subjects such as biological sciences is high at an undergraduate stage, the proportion decreases at each progression point – postgraduate, postdoctoral, lecturer – leaving very few females at the professorial level.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: justify;">Institutional biases or individual burdens?</h2>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Many explanations have been put forward to account for this disproportion – including institutional biases, implicit and direct discrimination, lack of role models or lack of confidence in the women themselves. However, <a href="http://ftp.iza.org/dp10947.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">research published in August</a> shows that women are in fact more resilient than one might expect. Factors such as high school academic preparation, faculty gender ratio, or performance in the core subjects appear to have an equal effect on males and females, in terms of the risk of switching majors. Stereotyping a field as ‘masculine’ also seems to have no profound effect on the women in it. However, while individual factors appear to have no effect, their combination – particularly low grades, gender composition of class and external stereotyping signals – is a strong enough hit to drive women to drop out. It might therefore be worth investigating the ways of making the external environment a bit more ‘female friendly’ on an institutional level.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: justify;">Creating a female-friendly field</h2>
<p style="text-align: justify;">One way of addressing gender inequality in British institutions is the <a href="http://www.ecu.ac.uk/equality-charters/athena-swan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Athena SWAN (Scientific Women’s Academic Network) charter.</a> Founded in 2005, it recognises and celebrates examples of good practice towards the advancement of gender equality in higher education and research. Some of the recognised actions include outreach and mentoring programmes, reducing bias in recruitment, devising flexible and part-time working schemes which ensure career progression or providing better access to childcare. Initially, the programme was limited to STEM subjects; currently it has expanded to include other disciplines.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Similarly, mobility schemes such as the <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/research/mariecurieactions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Marie Sklodowska-Curie Fellowship</a> allow women to actively pursue an international career in science. Traditionally, the mobility of female researchers has been lower than that of their male peers, as the career progression of women has often been adjusted to accommodate the needs of the family. However currently, in dual-career households, it is often the higher-earning partner who dictates the mobility strategy. Providing financial independence and promoting equal pay leads female scientists towards a much more international professional life.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">We are at a point in history when the tables are turning – women are finding themselves encouraged, supported, and are suddenly beginning to grasp at the opportunities that have thus far been less accessible to them. A diversity of backgrounds, beliefs and opinions is an important contribution to the development of any field – as is retaining the potential of highly qualified employees.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><em>Joanna Bagniewska is a Zoologist, Science Communicator and Teaching Fellow at the University of Reading in the UK. </em></p>
</section>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Podcast at the Sofia Science Festival: Would you ban trophy hunting in Africa?</title>
		<link>/2017/05/25/podcast-at-the-sofia-science-festival-would-you-ban-trophy-hunting-in-africa/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 20:19:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Radio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cecil the lion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hunting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sofia Science Festival]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1715</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Oxford graduate zoologist Dr Joanna Bagniewska, a teaching fellow at the School of Biological Sciences at the University of Reading, took an enraptured audience at the 2017 Sofia Science Festival through the debates on trophy hunting and conservation. Listen to the podcast with Bulgaria Now’s Lance Nelson and The Sofia Globe’s...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: justify;">Oxford graduate zoologist Dr Joanna Bagniewska, a teaching fellow at the School of Biological Sciences at the University of Reading, took an enraptured audience at the 2017 Sofia Science Festival through the debates on trophy hunting and conservation.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Listen to the podcast with Bulgaria Now’s Lance Nelson and The Sofia Globe’s Clive Leviev-Sawyer <a href="http://sofiaglobe.com/2017/05/14/podcast-at-the-sofia-science-festival-would-you-ban-trophy-hunting-in-africa/">here</a>.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The importance of sex in science</title>
		<link>/2017/03/29/the-importance-of-sex-in-science/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 11:25:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[My writing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gendered innovations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women in STEM]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1683</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[My post for Discov-Her, the L&#8217;Oreal Foundation blog. In science, what difference does sex make? Dr. Joanna Bagniewska, ecologist, well-known science communicator and teaching fellow at the University of Reading, is here to explain. I’m an ecologist – and ecologists talk about sex A LOT. We love to prod the...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: justify;"><em>My post for <a href="http://discov-her.com/en/article/the-importance-of-sex-in-science/bf01f45dfcfc20d20e4ee0a3dc7cd05e">Discov-Her</a>, the L&#8217;Oreal Foundation blog.</em></p>
<div id="intro" style="text-align: justify;"><strong>In science, what difference does sex make? Dr. Joanna Bagniewska, ecologist, well-known science communicator and teaching fellow at the University of Reading, is here to explain.</strong></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;"></div>
<div id="content">
<p style="text-align: justify;">I’m an ecologist – and ecologists talk about sex A LOT. We love to prod the underlying differences between sexes in different species. After all, why should we assume that males and females, which occupy different territories, have different diets and exhibit different behaviours, would be ecologically and evolutionarily identical?</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Consequently, in the scientific articles in my field, the sex of study animals is reported on a regular basis. I was very surprised to find out, however, that this attitude is quite different in other disciplines, e.g. in biomedical research.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Until recently, in medical studies, female animals were treated simply as male animals with hormonal fluctuations. Such an oversimplification is, unfortunately, very often inappropriate and insufficient. Just last year a group of international researchers, led by scientists from McGill University, showed that when it comes to pain, not only is there a difference in tolerance and sensitivity between the sexes – there are also fundamental physiological differences in dealing with it. In rodents, the two sexes actually use <a href="http://www.nature.com/neuro/journal/v18/n8/full/nn.4053.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">different immune cells</a> in the spinal cord to process the pain – T cells in females, and microglia in males. Yet, Jeffrey Mogil from McGill <a href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v535/n7611_supp/full/535S7a.html?WT.feed_name=subjects_neuroscience" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reports</a> that only 3 out of 71 scientific articles published in the journal Pain in 2015 confirmed the use of experimental rodents of both sexes; almost 80% used only male animals. <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0149763410001156" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Research</a> from UC Berkeley, led by Annaliese Beery, also showed a strong male bias in mammalian research in eight out of ten biological fields, most prominently in neuroscience. The authors suggest that studies focused solely on one sex should clearly indicate it in article titles.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">There is a flip side of the coin, too – the sex of the researchers themselves. In 2014, a <a href="http://www.nature.com/nmeth/journal/v11/n6/full/nmeth.2935.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">study</a> led by Robert Sorge, found that mice and rats used in experiments react differently to male and female researchers. When exposed to the scent of male humans, the rodents become very stressed – so much so, that such strong stress acts as an analgesic. What does it mean? Rodents (of both sexes) handled by male researchers may be less sensitive to pain, and, as a consequence, the sex of the experimenter may lead to differences in baselines in behavioural studies, on which further applied research is then founded. Unfortunately, most of the time the sex of the researcher is not reported in publications, making comparisons between studies difficult, if not impossible.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Discoveries such as those mentioned above lead to questions about their future applicability: types of pain medicine developed, dosages trialled in pain studies, and relevance to human subjects. And while the American Congress has introduced the <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/114th-congress/house-bill/2101" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Research for All Act</a>, requiring National Institutes of Health to run clinical trials on both men and women (in… 2015!), there is still a lack of consideration for sex in study animals, primary cells, or even cell lines.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Luckily the idea of gendered innovation, where gender and sex are incorporated into research principles, has been gaining recognition – largely due to the work of <a href="http://discov-her.com/en/article/the-importance-of-gendered-innovations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Londa Schiebinger</a> of Stanford University. Thanks to this approach, it turned out that osteoporosis – historically considered a predominantly female disease – can have very serious consequences for males; conversely, heart disease is not just a male problem – but is diagnosed differently in females.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">So… let’s talk about sex! Particularly in the context of good experimental design.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8211; Dr. Joanna Bagniewska</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brexit uncertainties threaten brain drain for UK science</title>
		<link>/2016/12/11/brexit-uncertainties-threaten-brain-drain-for-uk-science/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2016 22:22:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Associated Press]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brexit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[British science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EU]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1661</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A piece by Sylvia Hui, for Associated Press &#124; Like many foreign scientists in Britain, Joanna Bagniewska was devastated when Britons voted to leave the European Union. The biology lecturer, a Polish migrant who found Britain a welcoming place to build her academic career over a decade, is suddenly seeing her...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="articleContent" class="articleContent">
<div class="dtTitle">
<div class="dtTitleContainer">
<p class="topTitle" style="text-align: justify;"><em>A piece by Sylvia Hui, for <a href="https://apnews.com/aa7dae8a7c58415a8c5479782f514ae5/Brexit-uncertainties-threaten-brain-drain-for-UK-science?utm_campaign=SocialFlow&amp;utm_source=Twitter&amp;utm_medium=AP">Associated Press</a></em><a href="https://apnews.com/aa7dae8a7c58415a8c5479782f514ae5/Brexit-uncertainties-threaten-brain-drain-for-UK-science?utm_campaign=SocialFlow&amp;utm_source=Twitter&amp;utm_medium=AP"> </a><a href="https://apnews.com/aa7dae8a7c58415a8c5479782f514ae5/Brexit-uncertainties-threaten-brain-drain-for-UK-science?utm_campaign=SocialFlow&amp;utm_source=Twitter&amp;utm_medium=AP">|</a></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class=" articleImage modalImageButton " style="text-align: justify;">
<div class="articleIcons">Like many foreign scientists in Britain, Joanna Bagniewska was devastated when Britons voted to leave the European Union. The biology lecturer, a Polish migrant who found Britain a welcoming place to build her academic career over a decade, is suddenly seeing her job security and research prospects up in the air.</div>
</div>
<article id="contentArea" class=" ">
<div class="articleBody">
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8220;I&#8217;m worried that after my current contract finishes, one of the prerequisites could be a permanent residence card,&#8221; she said. &#8220;I&#8217;d like to apply for EU grant money, but how much longer will it be available for?&#8221;</p>
<p><span id="more-1661"></span></p>
<div class="ad-placeholder" style="text-align: justify;"></div>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Britain&#8217;s top universities have long been among the world&#8217;s most sought-after destinations for study and research, drawing the brightest minds from all corners of the globe. But since Britons voted in June to leave the 28-nation EU, many in the science community say the U.K. risks losing the money, the international influence — and crucially, the talent — to sustain that enviable position.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">More than one-tenth of research funding at British universities has come from the EU in recent years. Some fields — such as nanotechnology and cancer research — are more dependent on EU funding than others, according to a report by technology firm Digital Science. From 2007 to 2013, Britain received 8.8 billion euros ($9.4 billion) in direct EU investment in research.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Bagniewska is not just anxious about herself — she&#8217;s upset for her students&#8217; future too, for the opportunities that both Britons and foreigners will likely miss out on when unfettered mobility between Britain and Europe can no longer be taken for granted.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8220;They were just getting excited about doing their masters and Ph.Ds in other countries. And then Brexit happened and they just got trampled,&#8221; she said.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Scientists and researchers argue that being part of the EU has given British science a huge boost because it allows Britain to recruit the best talent across Europe and take part in important research collaborations and student exchanges without being constrained by national boundaries. The bloc&#8217;s freedom of movement means its 500 million people can live and work visa-free in any member state.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">No one knows yet what form Britain&#8217;s exit from the EU — commonly known as Brexit — is going to take, but immigration was a key issue for &#8220;Leave&#8221; voters. Many believe some limit should be put on the number of EU citizens moving to Britain.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Prime Minister Theresa May has vowed to reassert control over British borders. She has offered no firm guarantees for the rights of Europeans already living in Britain, an uncertainty that weighs heavily over the 32,000 Europeans who make up 16 percent of the academic workforce in British universities. Many universities say the rhetoric over immigration control is also jeopardizing recruitment of researchers and students from further afield.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Scientists for EU, an advocacy group, says it has received over 400 letters from researchers describing how Brexit has already impacted their life and work. Some are losing doctoral students who pulled out of studentships and job offers. Academics are putting plans to relocate to Britain on hold. One said their employer, a London university, immediately imposed a temporary hiring freeze, citing uncertainties about student recruitment and research income.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Adam Durrant, a British entrepreneur who founded an aerospace startup supplying climate data to airlines and aircraft manufacturers, says he&#8217;s now considering moving some of his business to a EU country outside of Britain. Part of the reason, he says, is that Brexit will likely make hiring the right people much harder than before.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8220;In the future, it probably means that people would be less interested to come to the U.K. to work,&#8221; said Durrant. &#8220;There&#8217;s a huge question mark over my company and my own personal future. I will certainly retain a U.K. presence, but my company&#8217;s focus of gravity may shift elsewhere.&#8221;</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Scientists say some U.K.-based researchers are already being excluded from joint bids for EU funding to minimize the risks for their colleagues.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Paul Crowther, head of physics and astronomy at the University of Sheffield, said a researcher from his department was dropped from an EU grant proposal as a precaution following the Brexit referendum. The vote &#8220;put the U.K.-based researchers in a very awkward position&#8221; and their participation in EU-funded programs could &#8220;compromise the project,&#8221; he was told.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8220;The erosion of U.K. involvement in EU networks has already begun, with both the U.K. and EU science worse off,&#8221; Crowther said.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Apart from a loss of grant money, Brexit will likely cause British scientists and research centers to miss out on shared databases and infrastructure.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8220;Large-scale efforts like studies of rare genetic diseases, the building of large facilities, are areas that multinational collaborations do much better,&#8221; said Venki Ramakrishnan, a Nobel Prize-winning biologist and president of Britain&#8217;s prestigious Royal Society.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The EU is an important source of research funding for Britain, which lags behind many developed countries in state investment in science. In 2014, Britain&#8217;s government spent under 0.5 percent of its GDP on research — below the European average, and half that of South Korea.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">May&#8217;s government is clearly aware of the jitters. She has promised to increase annual investment in research by 2 billion pounds ($2.4 billion) by 2020, in hopes her country can remain a world leader in science and innovation.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Durrant is doubtful that&#8217;s enough to make a big difference.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8220;Two billion a year spread across everything isn&#8217;t going to go very far,&#8221; he said.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Similar anxieties are being felt at the undergraduate level. The 125,000 European students studying at British universities now pay the same fees as locals and have access to the same government loans. Officials have promised this will not change for those applying next year — but no one knows what will happen after that.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Fewer European students appeared to be applying for some of Britain&#8217;s most competitive university courses, including medicine and places at Oxford and Cambridge. In September, the admission service UCAS reported a 9 percent drop in EU applications for British undergraduate courses starting in 2017.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Some argue that Britain could become like Switzerland, an &#8220;associate&#8221; EU state that is opting out of free movement of people while still taking part in limited European science projects.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8220;It&#8217;s not all doom and gloom — but it will be harder,&#8221; Ramakrishnan said. &#8220;We could make a go of it outside the EU. But for that to happen, we have to attract talent and fund science. And those two things are critical.&#8221;</p>
</div>
</article>
<div id="taboolaContainer" class="taboolaContainer" style="text-align: justify;"></div>
</div>
<div class="sideRail rightRail" style="text-align: justify;"></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>We’re not science automatons – we’re people: Meet Joanna Bagniewska</title>
		<link>/2016/07/10/were-not-science-automatons-were-people-meet-joanna-bagniewska/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2016 20:20:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Soapbox Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women in STEM]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1502</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[My interview for the Soapbox Science blog. Dr Joanna Bagniewska is a zoologist working as a teaching fellow at Reading University’s School of Biological Sciences. Her research interests encompass ecology and conservation biology, particularly the subject of invasive species. She is a very keen science communicator – she won FameLab Poland, gave a...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: justify;"><em>My interview for the <a href="http://soapboxscience.org/?p=3321">Soapbox Science blog</a>.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Dr Joanna Bagniewska is a zoologist working as a teaching fellow at <a href="https://www.reading.ac.uk/biologicalsciences/about/staff/j-m-bagniewska.aspx">Reading </a>University’s School of Biological Sciences. Her research interests encompass ecology and conservation biology, particularly the subject of invasive species. She is a very keen science communicator – she won FameLab Poland, gave a talk at TEDxWarsaw, and she even does science stand-up comedy.  Meet Joanna in our <a href="http://soapboxscience.org/?page_id=2560">Reading </a>event, where she’ll be discussing <em>“How Disney &amp; Science don’t always go hand in hand”.</em></p>
<div class="entry-content">
<p style="text-align: justify;"><em>SS: Joanna, how did you get to your current position?</em></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">JB: While completing my undergraduate in Biology at Jacobs University in Bremen, Germany, I did an internship with the University of New South Wales. I spent two months in Australia’s Snowy Mountains examining road ecology – i.e. the impact of roads on the surrounding wildlife. I found the subject absolutely fascinating, and from that point onwards I knew that I wanted to research ecology and conservation biology. To get more international experience, I decided to spend a semester abroad at Rice University in Texas, where I obtained a lot of hands-on experience in herpetology and animal behaviour. After completing my undergraduate degree, I went on to obtain my MSc from Oxford University; my research focused on the methods used for monitoring South African canid species, such as jackals and foxes. I then stayed at Oxford for my doctorate, which examined the behavioural ecology of the American mink in the UK. After graduating, I worked for a start-up company for a few months, and then went on to be a lecturer at Nottingham Trent University. Eventually I moved back to West Midlands to take the post of a teaching fellow at Reading University’s School of Biological Sciences.</p>
<p><span id="more-1502"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><em>SS: What, or who, inspired you to get a career in science?</em></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">JB: My earliest inspiration came from countless books on animals that I received from my parents when I was very little. I’ve always had very diverse interests, and up until the very end of high school I wasn’t sure what to study. I was torn between studying architecture (like my mother), Chinese language (because I lived in China for a few years) and animal science (because I really liked animals). Eventually I settled for biology, even though it was my weakest subject in school – mainly because I was very passionate about wildlife, but not any of the other aspects of the curriculum! Going to university was pretty much the default option in my family, but as I was the first one to choose a science degree, my parents were very apprehensive – they did not think that biology was a viable career choice. In fact, it was only when I went to South Africa with my students last year, my mother finally admitted “wow, you really do have the coolest job in the world”.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><em>SS: What is the most fascinating aspect of your research/work?</em></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">JB: There are several. Making sense of the world around us, interacting with animals, travelling, and finally meeting inspirational and passionate people.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><em>SS: What attracted you to Soapbox Science in the first place?</em></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">JB: Talking to people about what animals do is one of my favourite activities of all time. Well, that and ceilidhs.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><em>SS: Sum up in one word your expectations for the day – excitement? Fear? Thrill? Anticipation?</em></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">JB: Woohoo!</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><em>SS: If you could change one thing about the scientific culture right now, what would it be?</em></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">JB: The lack of stability. I understand that mobility is good for science, but I really don’t think it’s that good for scientists. We’re not science automatons – we’re people, we want to have relationships, start families, have a good night’s sleep without worrying about where our money will come from tomorrow. Continuous searches for funding, applying for grants, looking for jobs is what really sucks the fun out of science. Currently in some scientific circles revealing that you have a life outside of academia leads to, in the best case, a few funny looks, in the worst – being labelled a weak scientist.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><em>SS: What would be your top recommendation to a female PhD student considering pursuing a career in academia?</em></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">JB: I have a dilemma here. The optimistic advice would be: believe in what you do, be kind to everyone, and build a supportive contact network around you. The truly heartfelt (although painful) advice would be: find a rich husband/wife, prepare for an extremely competitive environment with very little money to go around, and always have an escape plan. I know the second set sounds incredibly harsh, but when I look back at my academic career, I wish someone had given me a reality check like this – not to put me down, but to really allow me to prepare myself for any worst case scenarios.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reading town centre to host Speaker&#8217;s Corner style science talks</title>
		<link>/2016/06/30/reading-town-centre-to-host-speakers-corner-style-science-talks/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 19:39:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Disney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Soapbox Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women in STEM]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://joannabagniewska.com/?p=1547</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[An advert for Soapbox Science on getreading.co.uk Take a look at some of these fascinating facts you could learn about at the Reading town centre event Would you let a zoologist tell you the truth about the animals in Disney films? Warning: you might not be able to watch them...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="row1" class="tmRow span-15-5 col-1 article-page">
<div class="tmCol article">
<div class="lead-text">
<p><em>An advert for Soapbox Science on <a href="http://www.getreading.co.uk/whats-on/whats-on-news/reading-town-centre-host-speakers-11546198">getreading.co.uk</a></em></p>
<h2 class="">Take a look at some of these fascinating facts you could learn about at the Reading town centre event</h2>
</div>
<div class="styleGroup "></div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="row2" class="tmRow span-15-5 col-1 article-page p402_hide">
<div class="tmCol article">
<div class="styleGroup "></div>
<figure class="inline-image clearfix ">
<div class="image-credit-wrapper"><img src="http://i4.getreading.co.uk/incoming/article11546710.ece/ALTERNATES/s615/Soapbox-Science.jpg" /></div>
</figure>
<div id="div-gpt-ad-inpage-video" class=""></div>
<div class="body ">
<p>Would you let a zoologist tell you the truth about the animals in Disney films? Warning: you might not be able to watch them in the same way ever again.</p>
<p>That&#8217;s what The University of Reading&#8217;s Dr Joanna Bagniewska will be doing at a Soapbox Science event at Reading town centre next weekend.</p>
<p>She will be telling children how Baloo from The Jungle Book isn&#8217;t as cuddly as he seems, and that Simba and Nala from The Lion King could actually be brother and sister &#8211; yeah, our minds are blown too.</p>
<p>The talk titled, How Disney and Science don’t always go hand in hand, is just one of the events sharing weird and wonderful facts at the science takeover in Reading on Saturday, July 9.</p>
<p>Bringing together professors from an array of environmental fields, the aim of the day is to promote female scientists who will be talking to audiences about some of the projects and ideas they have worked on.</p>
<p>Following the format of London Hyde Park’s Speaker’s Corner, the talks will run from midday to 3pm in Broad Street outside Sainsbury&#8217;s.</p>
<h3>For now, take a look at these fascinating facts &#8211; just some of things you can discover on the day</h3>
<ol>
<li>Overflows of untreated sewage into the River Thames adds up to tens of millions of tonnes every year. Each year, enough sewage discharges into the River Thames to fill the Albert Hall 450 times over.</li>
<li>The levels of drug materials found in rivers are used to estimate the amount of drugs consumed in towns and cities.</li>
<li>Mammals with large brains are more vulnerable to extinction. Big brains may help humans, but are bad news for other mammals.</li>
<li>Palm oil is found in about 50 per cent of all packaged supermarket products, from your peanut butter to your soap.</li>
<li>14 out of the 18 different species of bat species found in the UK have been recorded in Berkshire and South Buckinghamshire.</li>
</ol>
<figure class="inline-image clearfix "><img title="There are currently 18 species of bat living in the UK." src="http://i2.getreading.co.uk/incoming/article10058201.ece/ALTERNATES/s615b/bat.jpg" alt="" width="615" height="307" /><figcaption>There are currently 18 species of bat living in the UK.</figcaption></figure>
<h3>The programme for the day:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Dr. Emily Lines, Queen Mary University of London &#8211; Forecasting the future of forests</li>
<li>Ms Amanda Zillig, Atkins &#8211; What lies beneath, exposing contaminated land risks in exposed ground</li>
<li>Dr Joanna Bagniewska, University of Reading &#8211; How Disney and Science don’t always go hand in hand</li>
<li>Ms Betty Flora Nakiru, University of Sussex &#8211; Climate change and drought, how to maximise usage of limited water</li>
<li>Ms Patricia Tumwine, Arup &#8211; You Poo Toom, an introduction to the Thames Tideway Tunnel Project</li>
<li>Kathryn Woolley, Hilson Moran &#8211; How I create air pollution</li>
<li>Dr Victoria Hilborne, London South Bank University &#8211; Contamination of water with drugs and their metabolites</li>
<li>Ms Kirstie Scott, University College London &#8211; Environmental forensics: fighting crime with mud, bugs and plants!</li>
<li>Dr Manuela Gonzalez-Suarez, University of Reading The problems of having a big brain and other things that increase extinction risk</li>
<li>Dr Lydia Cole, University of Oxford &#8211; Peanut butter, palm oil and peat</li>
<li>Ms Erika Degani University of Reading &#8211; Food security: how can biodiversity help?</li>
<li>Kate Harrington, Arup &#8211; Bringing wildlife into cities, an ecologists approach to development</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
