<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>men &#8211; Dr JOANNA BAGNIEWSKA</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/men/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>zoologist &#124; science communicator </description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 12:05:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9.5</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Talking science in an engaging way</title>
		<link>/2014/05/20/talking-science-in-an-engaging-way/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 22:53:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joanna]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[In English]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[competition]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[men]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[physiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[talking science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[testicles]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://jbagniewska.wordpress.com/?p=669</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[NOTTINGHAM Trent University academic Dr Joanna Bagniewska has made it into the international rounds of a science communication competition. Joanna, a lecturer in wildlife conservation in the university&#8217;s School of Animal, Rural and Environmental Sciences, will compete against more than 25 other contestants after winning the national final of FameLab...]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NOTTINGHAM Trent University academic Dr Joanna Bagniewska has made it into the international rounds of a science communication competition.</p>
<p><span id="more-669"></span>Joanna, a lecturer in wildlife conservation in the university&#8217;s School of Animal, Rural and Environmental Sciences, will compete against more than 25 other contestants after winning the national final of FameLab in her native Poland.</p>
<p>The event challenges researchers to present a topic in science, engineering or maths in an engaging way to a non-specialist audience in just three minutes.</p>
<p>Her topic was &#8220;The curious incident of testicles at night time&#8221;, examining the influence of the melatonin hormone on the physiology of humans and other animals.</p>
<p>FameLab aims to &#8220;find the new voice of science and engineering across the world&#8221;.</p>
<p>Joanna, who will be representing Poland in the international round, said: &#8220;I am very pleased with the result, particularly because I usually do not use Polish to talk science.</p>
<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s been a challenge and a wonderful adventure, and I am looking forward to representing my country and Nottingham Trent University in the international rounds.&#8221;</p>
<p>Read more: <a style="color:#003399;" href="http://www.nottinghampost.com/Talking-science-engaging-way/story-21113738-detail/story.html#ixzz32IavbgPk">http://www.nottinghampost.com/Talking-science-engaging-way/story-21113738-detail/story.html#ixzz32IavbgPk</a></p>
<p>The scan of the printed copy can be seen <a href="http://jbagniewska.files.wordpress.com/2014/05/untitled.pdf">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
